<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="92"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[132]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[133]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[INTRODUCTION                                                                  137


                     3.1 WELL-DEFINED OBJECTIVES                                                   137

                     3.1.1 INTERNATIONAL AND LOCAL COLLABORATION AND LINKAGES OFFICE137


                     3.1.2 Goals of the University Extension Office                                138


                     3.1.3 Objectives of the University Extension Office                           139


                     3.1.4 Goals of The College of Arts and Sciences                               139


                     3.1.5 Objectives of the Bachelor of Science in Psychology Program             139


                     3.2 Adequate and Relevant Projects / Activities to Achieve Objectives         140

                     3.2. CVSU Internationalization Program                                        160


                     3.3 Systematic and Effective Procedures                                       166


                     3.4. Reasonable Budget                                                        170


                     3.5 Provision of Materials And Other Resources                                173

                     3.6 Participation of Significant Number Of Faculty / Staff / Student / Community In Major


                         Projects / Activities                                                     175

                     3.7 Outcomes                                                                  183


                     3.8 BEST PRACTICES ADOPTED                                                    191


                     Memorandum Of Understanding (Mou) / Memorandum Of Agreement (Moa)             199























                                                                  134]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[List of Tables




                   Table 3- 1 Extension Programs of the College                                              142

                   Table 3- 2. List of extension partners of the college                                     144


                   Table 3- 3 Extension Collaboration                                                        183

                   Table 3- 4  Academic Collaboration                                                        185


                   Table 3- 5   On-the-Job Training Partners                                                 190


































































                                                                  135]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[List of Figures


                   Figure 3- 1 Linkages framework of Cavite State University                                 141

                   Figure 3- 2 International House II                                                        162

                   Figure 3- 3 International House I                                                         162

                   Figure 3-  4  The  organizational  structure of  the  CvSU  Office of the  President showing the

                             Internationalization Program Unit                                               165


                   Figure 3- 5 Framework for Extension Process Flow                                          170

                   Figure 3- 6 CvSU MOOE FY 2017                                                             171

                   Figure 3- 7 Budget for the operation of Special Project Office                            172

                   Figure 3- 8 Budget for travelling expenses                                                173

                   Figure 3- 9 College of Arts and Sciences MOOE FY 2017                                     174













































                                                                  136]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[3: LINKAGES

                            RESEARCH UNIVERSITY IN 2022: STRENGTHENING CvSU LINKAGES



                   INTRODUCTION

                          To achieve the goals set by the University, the administrators, faculty, employees, and


                   students are  expected to  live  by  and  stand  for the  following University tenets:  TRUTH,

                   EXCELLENCE and SERVICE.

                          The University has been working hard towards internationalization, a global university.

                   For the last two decades, CvSU has built a solid foundation for its international recognition after

                   having strengthened its various academic programs through the establishment of numerous


                   local,  regional, national, and  international linkages in instruction, research and extension in

                   which it earned local, regional, and national recognitions.

                   3.1 WELL-DEFINED OBJECTIVES

                          Continuing  the  establishment  of  linkages  with  government  and  non-government

                   organizations has  been a  persistent effort of Cavite State  University in  strengthening the

                   academic,  research,  and  extension  programs.  Though  establishing  linkages  with  other

                   organizations may  involve cost in the institution, still it was prioritized as  it provides various


                   benefits. Through these linkages, support in terms of faculty and staff development, research

                   and extension grants, improvement of facilities and On-the-Job Trainings (OJT) Program for

                   students have been attained. Partnership and close collaboration  with these agencies through

                   the two university office, ICLO and  University Extension Office has provided opportunities for

                   the advancement of the institution.


                   3.1.1 INTERNATIONAL AND LOCAL COLLABORATION AND LINKAGES OFFICE

                          In line with  the  thrust to  improve  the  capabilities  of the university in    establishing

                   partnerships and linkages, a new office, the International and Local Collaboration and Linkages

                   Office by virtue of BOR Resolution No. 8, series of 2019  (ICLO)” replaced the Special Project

                   Office that was established by Board of Regents Resolution (BOR) No. 12 s. 2006.

                   Objective:




                                                                  137]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[The Office of International and Local Collaboration and Linkages Office (ICLO) shall be

                   concerned with  all  the  external  linkages  of  the  University particularly  those  covered by

                   Memorandum of Agreement (MOA) or Memorandum of Understanding (MOU).

                   Functions:

                      The ICLO has the following functions:


                          1.  Act  as  the  clearing  house  for  local  and  international  MOUs  and  MOAs  for

                             endorsement to the Administrative Council and Board of Regents;

                          2.  Identify and discuss issues to the Executive Council that may impact on University’s

                             Internationalization Strategy;

                          3.  Respond to  proposals  referred by  Colleges/Campuses  that  relate  to  local  and


                             international linkages;

                          4.  Ensure transfer of information, knowledge, and identification of linkages in both local

                             and international to the Academic Council of Colleges and Campuses;

                          5.  Provide forum for the development and exchange of good practices in international

                             and local activities;

                          6.  Serve as liaison officer in relation to local and international research and academic

                             collaboration with other agencies; and


                          7.  Manage all communication/ documents in relation to student and faculty exchanges,

                             study visit and the like between and among academic partners.

                   3.1.2 Goals of the University Extension Office

                         1.  Disseminate  and  promote  innovative,  relevant,  appropriate,  and  research-based

                            knowledge, information, and technologies to various clients;


                         2. Engage and enhance partnership with various stakeholders, local and international to

                            address the needs of target clients and the communities, and the resource limitation

                            of the extension organization; and

                         3. Enhance the organization’s capability to provide excellent and world class extension

                            services.







                                                                  138]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[3.1.3 Objectives of the University Extension Office

                         1.  Conduct and/or coordinate relevant training programs and short non-degree courses

                            in agriculture and other disciplines.

                         2.  Package  and  disseminate  through  tri-media  the  needed technology/ information

                            relevant to the improvement of the farming and rural/urban living.


                         3.  Coordinate and  monitor    the  extension activities  of various  colleges and  branch

                            campuses of the University.

                         4.  Promote agricultural entrepreneurship and other business enterprises.

                         5.  Establish  and  maintain  on-campus  and  off-campus  demonstration  projects

                            showcasing various appropriate technologies.


                         6.  Collaborate and establish linkages with government and private agencies engage in

                            extension and rural/urban development in the pursuit of common goals and objectives;

                            and

                        7.  Generate  income  from established  projects  and  from  other  resource generation

                            activities.



                   3.1.4 Goals of The College of Arts and Sciences


                          1. Cater relevant general education subjects and specialization courses in the arts and

                             sciences to  develop critically  minded and  morally  upright individuals  capable  of

                             meeting national and global demands;

                          2. Advanced sustainable research and extension in the arts and sciences responsive

                             to institutional, national, and global thrusts; and


                          3. Strengthen local and international partnership and linkages to promote professional

                             and social development.

                   3.1.5 Objectives of the Bachelor of Science in Psychology Program

                          1.  produce graduates who can apply psychological principles in analyzing structures of

                             society.







                                                                  139]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[2.  systematically  equip students with foundation of theories and practice for real-life

                             activities, research, and extension services.

                          3.  yield critical thinkers and creative workers for professional global competitiveness in

                             educational, industrial, and clinical settings.

                          4.  cultivate  professionally  competent,  morally  upright,  and  socially  responsible


                             individuals exposed to the various psychological situations; and

                          5.  hone  future  psychometricians,  psychologists,  counselors,  human  resource

                             managers, educators, and other psychological-helping professionals able to respond

                             to the demands of growing society.




                   3.2 Adequate and Relevant Projects / Activities to Achieve Objectives

                          The instruction, research, and extension activities  and projects of the College have

                   established  linkages  with  the  local,  regional,  national,  and  international  organizations or

                   agencies  over  the  years.  These  organizations  /  agencies  have  complemented  the

                   implementation  of  the  different  projects  /  activities  in  which  faculty  members  actively

                   participated in establishing linkages with the community, various institutions, local government,

                   non-government organizations, and  international  clientele. The  linkages  framework of the


                   University is presented in Figure 1. Linkages are subdivided into four categories: international,

                   national, regional, and local. These linkages are established to support the three functions of

                   the University which are instruction, extension, and research.





























                                                                  140]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[t
                                                            i
                                                           v
                                                             e
                                                                t
                                                               S

                                                     o

                                                   k
                                                      f
                                                         a
                                                        C

                                                                           r
                                                                          e
                                                                         v
                                                                            s
                                                                              y
                                                                              t
                                                                             i
                                                                   e
                                                                  t
                                                                 a

                                                                        i
                                                                       n
                                                                     U
                                                  r
                            -
                           3


                               L

                             1
                     i
                   F
                   Figure 3- 1 Linkages framework of Cavite State University
                     g
                         e
                        r
                       u
                                i

                                              e
                                        s
                                         f
                                            m
                                           a
                                          r
                                  k
                                 n
                                                 o
                                               w
                                      e
                                     g
                                    a






                                                                  141]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[In the last five years, the department under the Bachelor of Science in Psychology

                   program has implemented the following extension / program / activities. These activities were

                   facilitated with the assistance of various university offices tasked with extension and linkages.


                   Table 3- 1 Extension Programs of the College
                          Activity             Venue           Participants      Output


                    Values                 Indang  Habitat   43                  participants are able to:
                    Reorientation          Gangneung         Homepartners        1.  Grow as a member
                                           Pine   Village,                           of the community
                                           Brgy  Daine  2,                           and as a husband
                                           Indang, Cavite                            and wife
                                                                                 2.  Increase the value
                                                                                     of giving to the
                                                                                     community and
                                                                                     family
                                                                                 3.  Listen as of the
                                                                                     aspect in
                                                                                     empowering one
                                                                                     another and
                                                                                     eventually the
                                                                                     community of
                                                                                     IHGPV

                    Commitment       to    Indang Habitat    43        Home      participants should be
                    family,                Gangneung         partners                able to:
                    Commitment       to    Pine   Village,                       1.  .Identify physical,
                    Community              Brgy  Daine  2,                           mental, emotional
                    Psychology             Indang, Cavite                            differences
                    Seminar-                                                         between husband
                    Workshop  Series                                                 and wife.
                    for   Couples    of                                          2.  Discuss how
                    IHGPV                                                            couple differences
                                                                                     may used in
                                                                                     increasing couple
                                                                                     power towards
                                                                                     participation in
                                                                                     IHGPV activities
                                                                                     for community
                                                                                     development; and
                                                                                 3.  Appreciate varied
                                                                                     roles of husband
                                                                                     and wife in
                                                                                     building strong
                                                                                     family and
                                                                                     community ties,




                                                                  142]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[by creating role
                                                                                     plays to show the
                                                                                     lessons learned
                                                                                     and committing
                                                                                     oneself through
                                                                                     making their own
                                                                                     relationship vow
                                                                                     as couple part of
                                                                                     the community of
                                                                                     IHGPV

                    “Kaagapay        ng    Cavite   State    CHED Scholars       1.  establish
                    CHED Scholars”         University-                               strengths/needs/w
                    A          Modular     Main campus                               eaknesses of the
                    approach     to   a                                              participants.
                    Psychological                                                2.  strengthen the
                    Intervention    for                                              level of
                    Self-Empowerment                                                 awareness of the
                                                                                     participants
                                                                                 3.  strengthen the
                                                                                     capability of
                                                                                     elementary and
                                                                                     secondary school
                                                                                     teachers in using/
                                                                                     applying
                                                                                     biotechnology and
                                                                                     micro-techniques
                                                                                     in the conduct of
                                                                                     laboratory work;
                                                                                     and
                                                                                 4.  develop a positive
                                                                                     attitude on self-
                                                                                     confidence,
                                                                                     cooperative work
                                                                                     and team building
                                                                                     among
                                                                                     participants.



                          Table  3.1  enumerates  the  various  college  extension  activities  facilitated  by  local


                   linkages. The psychology program was involved in these activities that integrate the application

                   of its expertise.  The (Daine 2 IHGPV) program aimed to enhance positive value reorientation

                   that will bring about: a) Increased family’s livelihood opportunities for increased family income;

                   b)Increase in local governance’s level of leadership in community development activities; and




                                                                  143]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[c) Elevation of the client system from program recipients to program partners in  community

                   development.

                     Student and faculty of the department while conducting community needs assessment in
                                                  Brgy. Daine 1, Indang, Cavite






























                          Table 3.2 also  shows the linkages established by the college through its extension

                   activities.

                   Table 3- 2. List of extension partners of the college
                           AGENCY             ADDRESS                 LEVEL          NATURE OF LINKAGE
                    Local Government Unit –         Indang, Cavite            Local   Collaborating Agency
                     Daine 1, Indang, Cavite
                       Daine Western Cavite   Daine 1, Indang, Cavite         Local    Collaborating Agency
                                  Institute
                       St. Gregory the Great        Indang, Cavite            Local   Collaborating Agency
                              Parish (SGP)
                     Local Government Unit-         Indang, Cavite            Local    Collaborating Agency
                             Indang, Cavite

                     Kiwanis Club Treasures         Indang, Cavite      International   Food, Books, raffle
                                of Indang

                          Christian Mission   San Roque, Naic, Cavite   International
                         Service Philippines
                                  (CMSP)                                                  Two sacks of rice

                      Select Connect Union        Gangneung City        International    One unit of computer
                                                 Republic of Korea                           with essential
                                                                                              accessories









                                                                  144]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Awards and recognitions given to Daine 1 (linkage partner)













                                                                  145]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[The  Department of Social  Sciences and  Humanities  through its  psychology faculty and

                   students also established linkages with international and  national organizations in which students

                   and faculty members had attended different training and conferences. These are the following:

                          1.  Psychological Association of the Philippines

                          2.  Philippine Guidance and Counseling Association


                          3.  Philippine Mental Health Association

                          4.  The Edukcircle International Education Circle ICCS

                          5.  Peer Organization of the Philippines

                          6.  Association  of  Psychological  and  Educational  Counsellors of  The  Asia-pacific

                              (APECA)




























































                                                                  146]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[BS































                    Psychology instructors attending the 15th EdukCircle Convention in Psychology and Media
                                                     Communication in 2017

















































                                                                  147]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[BS Psychology instructor Dr Paulito Hilario as panel reactor in the Philippine Guidance and
                       Counseling Association Inc. 2018 International and 54th Annual National Conference




























                     Dr Paulito Hilario, attended Mental Health Facilitation Trainers Training by Association of
                    Psychological and Educational Counsellors of The Asia-pacific (APECA) and National Board
                                               of Certified Counselors (NBCC) USA











                                                                  148]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Dr. Cecilia Banaag served as the Board Member of  2016 Philippine Guidance and
                                                   Counseling Association Inc.
















                                                                  149]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Dr Paulito Hilario served as a moderator at the 2016 PTECHS Conference in National Chi
                                                     Nan University, Taiwan

















                                                                  150]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Ms.
                                                                                                         Mary
                                                                                                        Joyce

























                     Talamante, psychology instructor, and BS Psychology Students, attended a meeting with
                    representatives from other universities for the Peer Organization of the Philippines - Cavite
                                                             Chapter





































                      Ms. Jasmin Paras (5th from the left) and Mr. Ron Gabriel A. Peji (2nd from the right), BS
                    Psychology students and pioneer members of Peer Organization of the Philippines (PGCA-
                         affiliate), attending the first POP annual convention at the Heritage Hotel- Manila.









                                                                  151]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Moreover, BS  Psychology students had  undergone on-the-job training with various

                   agencies which resulted in the creation of an academic-industry partnership. Such practice

                   intends to expand the student’s knowledge, improve their skills, and instill positive work attitude

                   which will develop them into becoming globally competitive individuals.
























                       Ms. Jezreel Del Espiritu Santo, internship coordinator, conducting on-the-job training
                                  orientation to 4  year BS Psychology students, A.Y. 2019-2020
                                                th

                          The training partners of the college are as follows:



                    AFP Medical Center
                    Alfamart Trading Philippines, Inc.

                    Alta Monde Services Phils Corp
                    AMA Computer University

                    Analog Devices

                    Ankong Holdings Inc.
                    Asia Medic Family Hospital and Medical Center

                    Auto Delta Coach Builders Inc.
                    Be Connected Management Services (Bench)
                    Bridgehall Rehabilitation Center, Inc.

                    Bulihan Site Project Elementary School
                    Bureau of Internal Revenue




                                                                  152]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Camp Benjamin (We Lead Group Holding Inc.)
                    Cavite Center for Mental Health
                    Cavite National High School - Senior High School

                    Cavite National Science High School
                    Cavite Provincial Capital - Provincial Public Employment

                    Office
                    Cavite Provincial Capitol
                    Cebu General Services Inc.

                    Centro Escolar University - Makati
                    Change and Recovery Treatment and Rehabilitation Center

                    Chateau Royale
                    City College of Tagaytay
                    Civil Service Commission - Cavite

                    Clinic of the Holy Spirit
                    Coca-cola FEMSA Philippines, Inc. Dasma

                    Conduent: Business Process Services
                    Congressional Integrated High School
                    Convergys - Calamba

                    Convergys Singapore Holding Inc.
                    Craftsmind Outsource Solutions, Inc.
                    Crofil Manpower Services Contractor Corporation

                    Dasmariñas Integrated High School
                    Dasmariñas Integrated High School Main
                    De La Salle University - Dasmariñas

                    De la Salle University - Health Sciences Institute
                    Department of Health Treatment and Rehabilitation Center,

                    Tagaytay
                    Development Academy of the Philippines
                    Development Bank of the Philippines Service Corporation

                    Divine Grace Medical Center
                    Eds Manufacturing Inc.
                    Enomoto Philippine Manufacturing Inc.

                    EPeople Manpower Services Inc.
                    Erjohn & Almark Transit Corporation
                    EXL Service Philippines Inc.

                    Extraordinaire Janitorial and Manpower Services Incorporated
                    Far Eastern College




                                                                  153]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[FCIE Association Management
                    Fiat Lux Academe
                    First Filipino Saint Hospital (San Lorenzo Ruiz Hospital)

                    Fortunecross Phils., Inc.
                    FTN Garments Corporation

                    Gentri Medical Center and Hospital Inc.
                    Golden Arches Development Corporation
                    Golden Jewel Manpower Agency

                    Gourmet Farm
                    Harada Automotive Antenna Phil's Inc.

                    Harmo Technology Corporation
                    Heart of Jesus Rehabilitation Center
                    Helping Hand Development Cooperative

                    Heru Human Resource Specialist Company
                    Hiblow Phils Inc.

                    Higher Power (HP) Place Inc.
                    Hightower Inc.
                    Hocheng Philippines Corporation

                    Imus National High School - Main Campus
                    Indang Water District
                    Industrial Galvanizer Corporation of the Philippines

                    Insular Life
                    International Precision Assemblies Inc.
                    iQor

                    J.A. Services Cooperative
                    Jazy Policrete Inc

                    Jesse Care Pest Management Services
                    Jesus Son of Mary Academy
                    Jose R. Reyes Memorial Medical Center

                    Junction Tagaytay Hotel
                    Kerry Logistics (Phils.), Inc.
                    KLT Fruits, Inc.

                    Korea - Philippines Friendship Hospital
                    Kumkang Ceramics
                    Landbank of the Philippines Resources and Development

                    Corporation
                    LEENTech Network Solution




                                                                  154]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[LGU - Alfonso
                    LICA Auto Group (LICA Group of Companies)
                    Lifeline Rehabilitation Center

                    Linaheim Corporate Services Inc.
                    Liwayway Foods Corporation

                    Lord's Agape Recovery Center
                    Lumampong National High School
                    Lyceum of the Philippines University

                    M. V. Santiago Medical Center
                    Maxim de Humana International Inc.

                    MDGI Philippines Inc.
                    Metro Psychiatry Inc.
                    Metro Retail Stores Group Inc.

                    Metro, Imus
                    Mi Department Store

                    MIROF Resources, Inc.
                    Mitsobishi Phils. Corp
                    Mitsuwa Chemical Philippines, Inc.

                    MK Slider Phils Corp
                    MKP, Inc.
                    Newly Ever Rise Electronic Philippines

                    Nissan Corporation Dasmarinas
                    Notre Dame of Trece Martires
                    On Semiconductor Carmona Philippines

                    One Place Tagaytay
                    Our Lady of Remedios Montessori School

                    Our Lady of the Holy Rosary School, Tanza Cavite
                    Pasig Industries, Inc.
                    Perpetual Help System DALTA-Molino Campus

                    Philippine Bobbin Corporation
                    Philippine National Bank
                    Phoenix Petroleum, Inc.

                    Physician's Diagnostic Services Center
                    Pro-Excel Property Inc.
                    Provincial Government of Cavite - Human Resource

                    Management Office
                    PSI Technologies Inc.




                                                                  155]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[RCJV Inc.
                    Reliance Apparel and Fashion Manufacturing Corporation
                    Riviera Golf Club Inc.

                    ROC.ph Digital Marketing Services
                    Rosario Institute

                    RVN Construction Int'l Inc.
                    Saint Jude Parish School
                    Sangley Point Naval Base

                    Se jung Apparel Inc.
                    Self-Enhancement for Life Foundation

                    Serene Persona Enhancement Center
                    Serenity House of Sobriety
                    Service Resource Inc.

                    Shepherd Drug Rehabilitation
                    Shinryo Philippines Company, INC

                    Smartfuture Tech Inc.
                    Solaire Resort and Casino
                    Springwells of Hope Inc.

                    Starjob Multi-purpose Cooperative
                    Stoneworks Specialist International Corporation
                    Suminac Philippines Inc.

                    Tagaytay City National High School
                    Tagaytay City Science National High School
                    Tagaytay Highlands

                    Tanza National Comprehensive High School
                    Technomotion Controls, International, Inc.

                    Tencentech Inc.
                    The Lake Hotel
                    The Medical City Ortigas

                    Topserve Service Solutions, Inc.
                    Trece Martires City National High School
                    Trece Water District

                    University of Perpetual Help System DALTA-Molino Campus
                    Uny Pacific Manufacturing Corporation
                    Virlanie Foundation, Inc.







                                                                  156]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[157]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Scheduled Visit to Linkage Establishments






































































                    BS Psychology students facilitating psychosocial activities during their on-the-job training in
                                 the linkage institution during the Summer Term, A.Y. 2017-2018








                                                                  158]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Ms. Jezreel Espiritu Santo, OJT coordinator, Mary Joyce Talamante, Mr. John Paolo

                   Christian Belen, and Mr. Jhunar John Tauy, psychology instructors, visiting the linkage


                   institutions for the trainees’ case presentations during the Summer Term, A.Y. 2018 - 2019







                                                                  159]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[3.2. CVSU Internationalization Program

                          To become a global university, the first step in the strategy of the University started with

                   the Study Abroad Program (SAP) when representatives from Yeungjin College, South Korea

                   signed an agreement for the promotion of educational and academic exchanges between the

                   two institutions  which later followed by faculty and student exchanges, research collaboration,


                   and cultural ties.








































































                                                                  160]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[BS Psychology students and other student volunteers served as tutors in the English
                                         Proficiency Program for foreign students in 2019



                          This collaboration was first in the University and then became the model approach for

                   the internationalization program of the institution. Another strategy was  the creation of the

                   University  website  (www.cvsu.edu.ph)  that  gives  an  opportunity  to  international

                   organizations/institutions/agencies to connect with the university. More recently, MOUs were

                   signed  by  CvSU  with  Kansai  University,  the  National  Penghu University  of Science  and

                   Technology and  Edu  Connect Southeast Asia  Association  for collaborative  activities  (see


                   attached copies of MOAs and MOUs).

                          The  establishment  of  the  CvSU  website  (www.cvsu.edu.ph) in  2004  became  the

                   University’s window to the world and placed CvSU in the information map. This paved the way

                   for the easy access of information by students, researchers, professors, and business leaders

                   from other countries to the various program offerings of the University in instruction, research,

                   and  extension.  This  enabled  the  University  to  establish  contact  and  communicate  with


                   interested foreign students, universities, scholarship donors, research donors, development




                                                                  161]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[agencies, NGOs, GOs, and even private individuals. The International Houses I and II were

                   also constructed in order to provide transient housing, lecture/training halls and dining areas

                   for foreign students, faculty, and staff. Both buildings are equipped with internet facilities (see

                   Figures 3.2 and 3.3).




























                   Figure 3- 3 International House II






























                   Figure 3- 2 International House I

















                                                                  162]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[For  three years  from  2004-2006, the  Study  Abroad  Program  was  managed  and

                   spearheaded by the Continuing Education and Training Services (CETS) of the Office of the

                   Vice-President for Research, Extension, and  Continuing Education  and  Training  Services

                   (RECETS) under the supervision of Dr. Ruperto S. Sangalang, former University President.

                          At  the same  time,  the Commission  on Higher  Education has  also  recognized that


                   “globalization, changing foreign policies, and liberalization of trades in  goods and  services

                   worldwide” have created climate for borderless teaching and learning and has prolonged the

                   opportunities for transnational  education  which  includes establishment  of universities and

                   colleges abroad, higher education franchising and distance education (Papa, 2004, CETS).

                          Having  enhanced  and  developed  its  capability  in  teaching,  information  and


                   communication technologies, and open learning strategies, CvSU is ready for globalization.

                   With this, the CvSU Transnational Education Center was established by virtue of BOR No. 96

                   s 2006 on December 21, 2006 to serve as “trans-education and training provider where real or

                   virtual movement of teachers, students, course of study and academic programs from CvSU

                   to other countries and vice versa, are in place” (Papa, 2005, CETS).

                          The International Education  and  Training Center (IETC), formerly CvSU-TEC, also

                   served as the marketing support of CvSU higher education programs and short term courses


                   to Korea, Japan,  Thailand, and China with a  solid linkage with Foreign Higher Educational

                   Provider (FHEP). At this time, thousands of Koreans, Japanese, and Chinese students have

                   been trained in the University under different short training courses.

                          The establishment of CvSU-IETC was  followed by the conceptualization in 2006 of

                   CvSU  International  Programs  and  Linkages  Project  (IPLP)  to  enhance  and  lead  the


                   international strategy of the University in accordance with the University goal of becoming a

                   research university by    2022. It  was  regarded to be  based  at  the  CvSU-IETC  as  a  semi-

                   autonomous unit of the institution to attend to the fast-emerging market in international and

                   global education.

                          The  IPLP  provided the  needs  of  International  agencies,  institutions,  groups,  and

                   individuals pursuing to establish partnership, cooperation, and management services of the




                                                                  163]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[University by developing international programs that suits the needs of the international clients,

                   creating linkages with foreign institutions, serving as link between the concerned units of the

                   University and potential partners and students, liaising between the foreign institutions, and the

                   University, and generating resources from donors, partners, and co-operators.

                          The program is  the coordinating, monitoring, and  supervising unit of the University


                   covering all  aspects  of instruction, research, and  extension. The  tasks  of the  IPLP  were

                   numerous and the challenges were daunting; hence, it was only in 2008 when the IPLP was

                   institutionalized by the virtue of BOR Resolution No. 121 s. 2008 on November 26, 2008.

                          The creation of the IPLP was short-lived when in January of 2009 the project and the

                   International Education and Training Center where it was  based rationalized and merged as


                   one to be known as the CvSU Internationalization Program by virtue of BOR Resolution No.

                   135 s  2009 on January  19, 2009. The program  was  placed under the  Office of the  Vice

                   President for External and Business Affairs with the same functions and responsibilities. The

                   CvSU Internationalization Program had its office at the External and Business Affairs.

                          Establishing the capability  and  the readiness of the  University and  earning a  good

                   reputation internationally as an institution of quality education that is globally competitive were

                   the most tedious and difficult part of the internationalization efforts. The university had to count


                   years  and  decades  before  finally  CvSU  developed  its  English  teaching  competency,

                   information and communication capabilities, open learning strategies and finally, got noticed

                   by countries in Asia and the world. The Office of the President allocated much of the resources

                   of the presidency behind the enormous efforts of the  External and Business Affairs, deans and

                   faculty  members  of  the  different  colleges  and  campuses  to  establish  the  necessary


                   international infrastructure and linkages that realized the CvSU Internationalization Program.

                   Cavite State University’s path towards internationalization

                          There is  a  growing expectation for universities to get involved in  international and  global

                   education, that is, for the universities to produce graduates who can work in multicultural settings

                   and who can adapt to the fast-changing environment of critical thinking.







                                                                  164]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Cavite  State  University, in  its  bid  to  achieving  its  vision  and  participation  in  the global

                   education established the International and Local Collaboration and Linkages Office by virtue of BOR

                   Resolution No. 8, series of 2019, “approving the proposed restructuring of the office of the University

                   President, which to include the International and Local Collaboration and Linkages Office (ILCLO)”.




                                                 Office of the President







                                              Staff













                                         Director for                       OIC, Gender         Director for
                        Director for     Public Affairs    Director for         and            International
                        Presidential                                                            and Local
                       Management           and           Alumni Affairs    Development        Collaborations
                                        Communicatio         Office           Resource
                     Coordinating Office                                                       and Linkages
                                          ns Office                           Center
                                                                                                  Office

                    Figure 3- 4 The organizational structure of the CvSU Office of the President showing
                    the Internationalization Program Unit
                          The University, with its vision to become a  Global University, is focusing on the following

                   major areas in terms of local and international collaboration: 1) student mobility; 2) faculty mobility;


                   3)  research  collaboration;  4)  capacity  development  including  benchmarking;  and,  5)  industry

                   partnership and/or community engagement partnership.

                          These internationalization efforts would bring about new opportunities in the international

                   environment which are deemed to be necessary for the University’s continuous plan of creating a

                   globally-competitive environment and borderless education.














                                                                  165]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[3.3 Systematic and Effective Procedures

                          Cavite State University - Research Development and Extension Agenda Plan (RDEAP)

                   evolved through the following integrated and participatory procedures:

                          a.  Research, Extension, and Continuing Education and Training Services (RECETS)

                             conducts a  planning workshop. The  RECETS  spearhead  the  formulation of the


                             RDEAP through a workshop. Participants in this planning workshop are the Deans

                             of  the  different Colleges  and  branch  campuses  together with  their  respective

                             Research, Development and Extension (RDE) coordinators.

                          b.  During the University Planning workshop, the thrust of the University is reviewed and

                             revised. In this process, identification and selection of research and extension thrusts


                             are guided by the stated vision and mission of the university / college /  campus.

                             Likewise, the  Millennium  Development  Goals  (MDGs),  national  and  provincial,

                             municipal, and local development goals are considered.

                          c.  The research, development, and extension (RDE) thrusts resulting from the latest

                             (2004)  RDEAP  planning  workshops include:  poverty  alleviation,  food security,

                             primary  health  care  and  public  health,  alternative  medicine,  cultural  heritage

                             preservation,  ecosystem  management,  energy  conservation  and  utilization,


                             institutional  capability  building,  information  and  communication  technology,

                             infrastructure  planning  and  design,  biotechnology,  industrial  technology,

                             pedagogy/andragogy, gender and development, coffee, pineapple, banana, kaong,

                             makapuno, herbs and spices, ornamentals, and urban agriculture.

                          Prior to the actual conduct of the RDEAP planning workshop, the RDE coordinators


                   present their draft plans with their respective deans for further comments and suggestions.

                   During the workshop, the RDE  coordinators polish  their prepared agenda.  As  part of the

                   workshop, the RDEAP  of the different colleges / campuses are  presented to the RECETS

                   Council for comments and suggestions.

                          Also,  during  the presentation of  various  agenda  and  programs  by  the  colleges  /

                   campuses, duplication of plans and programs are eliminated. In cases where similar areas of




                                                                  166]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[concern are  presented by  two  or  more  colleges, either  one  party  will  drop its  proposed

                   knowledge area  or integrate such with the others of similar  nature.   Also, group members

                   openly discuss and decide as to who would lead in the implementation of such programs.

                          Deans  endorse the  corrected copy  of  their  RDEAPs  to  the  Research  Center for

                   consolidation. RDE coordinators incorporate the comments and suggestions made during the


                   presentation. The  deans  submit  the  corrected copy  to  the  Research Center  Council for

                   consolidation.

                          a.  Research Center collects the RDEAPs of the different colleges. The RDEAP of the

                              different colleges / campuses are consolidated by the Research Center into one

                              University RDEAP for the final review of the RECETS Council members.


                          b.  RECETS Council endorses the University RDEAP to the Administrative Council.

                              The RECETS Council through the VP-RECETS, who chairs the council, endorses

                              the RDEAP to the Administrative Council for Approval of the Board of Regents.

                          c.  Administrative Council endorses and recommends for approval of the RDEAP to the

                              Board of Regents.

                          d.   BOT approves the RDEAP.

                          e.   RECETS provides the approved RDEAP to concerned offices.


                          The  Department  follows  a  schematic  diagram  defined  by  the  CAS-IRDEAP  in

                   implementing research and extension projects in establishing linkages. In the framework, all

                   research / extension projects shall be properly endorsed by the concerned office or authority.

                   The memorandum  of agreement (MOA) or memorandum  of understanding (MOU) shall be

                   executed for the projects involving external partners. It also establishes linkages through on-


                   the-job training of BS Psychology students to various agencies. The establishment of linkages

                   is  facilitated and  coordinated by the designated college / department OJT coordinator. BS

                   Psychology Alumni  also  contributed to  the establishment  of linkages  with  their respective

                   employers.









                                                                  167]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[The extension program of the Department of Social Sciences and Humanities is based

                   on the need’s assessment, problems, and resources of the adopted community. The activities

                   are well-guided by the local, regional, and national development thrust and directions.


































                    Dr. Paul V. Hilario during a DSSH consultation with Municipal Risk and Disaster Reduction
                                                     Office of Alfonso Cavite

































                     DSSH faculty members during consultation with Barangay Asis leaders of  Mendez Cavite








                                                                  168]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[The  University  provides a  venue  for the  presentation of  on-going and  completed

                   Research / Extension Projects in the local, national, and international fora, symposium, and

                   conferences.

                          The College through its RDE coordinators and Dean, facilitates the conduct of its local

                   in-house review and  encourages the  faculty researchers and  extension task  force in the


                   presentation to the University In-House Review and Evaluation.

                          Recommendations  given  during  the  in-house  review  and  evaluation  and  regular

                   consultation with experts in the field and extension coordinators provided a wider room for

                   areas  of improvement and development of its  strengths. Generally, the  College hopes to

                   ensure the sustainability development of the extension projects and its impact to the clientele


                   in aspects that relate to providing quality life in the community and measuring the capabilities

                   and extent of transfer of technology and knowledge among the clientele.






















































                                                                  169]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[The College has devised a monitoring and evaluation form that is administered to the

                   clientele to determine the strengths and  weaknesses of the extension project and identify

                   possible rooms for improvement.

                                                                                                          3.4.



















































                        Figure 3- 5 Framework for Extension Process Flow

                   Reasonable Budget

                          The budget for establishing and enhancing academic, research, and extension linkages

                   is  included in  the financial plan  of the university. The budget for establishing linkages for

                   research activities is  also  covered by the funds generated by the  funding agencies to the


                   university. The university also  provided a  budget for then for the   operation of the Special

                   Project Office. To enable the faculty members and staff to engage in establishing international

                   linkages, the University also provides a substantial budget for travelling expenses. In addition,





                                                                  170]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Figure 3- 6 CvSU MOOE FY 2017
                   the college allocates from the MOOE budget for establishing linkages. It also conducted various


                   income-generating activities that will be used in different extension activities of the college.








                                                                  171]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[Figure 3- 7 Budget for the operation of Special Project Office




















                                                                  172]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Figure 3- 8 Budget for travelling expenses

                   3.5 Provision of Materials And Other Resources

                          The College of Arts and Sciences has allocated a budget amounting to Php 80,000.00

                   yearly for the establishment of its linkages. The fund allocated is a portion from the College’s

                   MOOE for research and extension works (Figure 3.9).

























                                                                  173]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[Figure 3- 9 College of Arts and Sciences MOOE FY 2017




























                                                                  174]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[3.6 Participation of Significant Number Of Faculty / Staff / Student / Community In Major

                   Projects / Activities



                          The research and extension activities of the college will not materialize without the help

                   of individuals/groups particularly during its formulation and implementation phase. A number


                   of faculty, students, community, and collaborating partners have participated in accomplishing

                   the goals of the research and extension projects.


































                     Faculty members attend and participate in a meeting to formulate Psychological First Aid
                    response of CvSU CAS with collaboration of Dr. Rezin Bahia Graduate School Dean last 15
                                                          January 2020






























                                                                  175]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[Volunteers from Psychology Program Faculty and Students in repacking efforts of DSWD
                                                             Mendez























                                                                  176]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[Psychological First Aid Services given by
                                                           Psychology Faculty and Students in Mendez Cavite





















                                                                  177]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[College of Arts and Sciences’ Research and Extension Coordinators and the dean,
                             Dr. Bettina Joyce P. Ilagan, during their planning for the research and extension
                                                                activities

































                   College of Arts and Sciences Extension Coordinators and Student Leaders while planning for
                                                 the extension projects/activities













                                                                  178]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[Faculty, parents, alumni, students, and representatives from the linkage partners during the
                                curriculum review of the BS Psychology Program, A.Y. 2017-2018




































                         Mrs. Normita D. Ayos, RPsyc from the Cavite Center for Mental Health during the
                                             collaborative seminar with PsycheGuide










                                                                  179]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[Dr. Maria Caridad Taroja was invited as one of the speakers in the seminar collaboration with
                                                           PsychGuide







































                      Student and other professionals attended the seminar collaboration with PsycheGuide







                                                                  180]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Ms. Armi Grace Desingano, Program Coordinator, receiving an original TAT from
                                    PsycheGuide as a token of gratitude for their collaboration




































                          BS Psychology student volunteers as staff during the collaboration seminar with
                                                          PsycheGuide













                                                                  181]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[Dr. Bettina Joyce P. Ilagan together with the members of PsycheGuide























































                                                                  182]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[3.7 Outcomes

                   Table 3- 3 Extension Collaboration

                      NATURE OF            ROLE OF THE              ROLE OF            BENEFIT(S) FROM
                       LINKAGE               COLLEGE               PARTNER(S)            PARTNERSHIP
                    Local           ●  Spearhead the        ●  Ensure participation of  ●  Strengthen and
                    Government Unit    implementation of the   target clients         developed strong
                    –                  project “Community                             collaboration,
                    Barangay  Daine    Adoption Services:   ●  Provide support in the   cooperation partnership
                    1, Indang, Cavite    Kabarangay at Kaeskwela   implementation of the   with SUCs, GOs, and
                                       Project                 project                NGOs in the
                    Extension                                                         implementation of the
                    Collaboration    ●  Sponsor             ●  Provide assistance     projects
                                       seminars/workshop/training  during the conduct of
                                       s in coordination with the   seminar/trainings/worksh   Encouraging inter-agency
                                                                                  ●
                                       CvSU Extension Services   ops and other related   partnership in the
                                       Unit and concerned      activities             development of the
                                       colleges                                       community newspaper to
                                                            ●  Provide assistance in the   promote the
                                    ●  Provide technical       establishment of       achievements of the
                                       assistance throughout the   demonstration projects, if   community
                                       duration of the project    necessary
                                                                                  ●   Opportunity for faculty
                                    ●  Establish linkages with   ●  Help in sourcing out   and students to gain
                                       government and non-     funds/donations/grants   actual experience in
                                       government agencies for   for the project      community organizing,
                                       possible tie-ups                               conduct of training and
                                                                                      conduct of community
                                    ●  Help in sourcing out                           needs assessment and
                                       funds/donations/grants for                     impact studies of
                                       the projects                                   extension projects

                                    ●  Regularly monitor and
                                       evaluate the project
                                       activities in coordination
                                       with the CvSU Extension
                                       Unit

                    Daine   Western  ●   Endorse all necessary   ●   Invite student participants  Strengthening the strong

                                                                                  ●
                    Cavite Institute    documents, proposals, and  to the activities that will   partnership and
                                       program of activities for   be conducted       collaboration with the
                    Extension          their approval                                 SUCs, GOs, and NGOs
                    Collaboration                          ●   Shall provide alternate   in the delivery of projects
                                   ●   Prepare the training design  venue for the conduct of   and programs for
                                       for the collaborative activity  the activities    community development
                                       for approval
                                                           ●   Monitor holding and   ●   Strengthening inter-
                                   ●   Provide resource person   completion of learning   agency
                                       and resource materials for   session           partnership/collaboration
                                       every learning                                 efforts to deliver literacy
                                       session/seminar/workshop                       among the youth

                                   ●   Establish linkage with other               ●   Set policy and direction
                                       commercial/government/N                        for the enhancement of
                                       GO for additional support                      learning

                                   ●   Responsible in the design
                                       and preparation of
                                       certificates of the
                                       participation to the
                                       participants

                    St.  Gregory  the ●   Prepare the training design  Establish linkages with ●   Strengthen partnership
                                                           ●
                    Great    Parish    to cater the needs of the   other              with St. Gregory the
                    (SGP)              organization for the    commercial/government/  Great Parish for
                                       approval of all stakeholders                   extension collaboration
                                                            183]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[Extension                                  NGOs for additional
                    Collaboration   ●   Establish linkage with other  support     ●   Opportunity for faculty
                                       commercial/government/N                        and students to gain
                                       GOs for possible additional  Provide for the learning   actual experience in
                                                           ●
                                       support                 venue at all times     community organizing,
                                                                                      conduct of training and
                                   ●   Provide for resource   ●   Monitor and evaluate the   conduct of community
                                       persons and learning    activities             needs assessment and
                                       guides along the skills                        impact studies of
                                       necessary for the                              extension projects
                                       preparation of IEC
                                       materials, PR and public
                                       information, free of charge
                                       to the participants

                                   ●   Responsible in the
                                       preparation and printing of
                                       certificate of participation to
                                       stakeholders and other
                                       participants to the project

                                   ●   Monitor and evaluate the
                                       activities
                    Local          ●   Spearhead the       ●   Ensure support in the   ●  Strengthen and
                    Government Unit    implementation of the   implementation of the   developed strong
                    – Indang, Cavite    project “Community     project                collaboration,
                                       Adoption Services:                             cooperation, and
                    Extension          Kabarangay at Kaeskwela ●   Help in sourcing out   partnership with SUCs,
                    Collaboration      Project                 funds/donations/grants   GOs, and NGOs in the
                                                               for the project        implementation of the
                                   ●   Sponsor                                        projects
                                       seminars/workshop/training   Provide assistance in the
                                                           ●
                                       s in coordination with the   conduct of extension  ●   Encouraging inter-agency
                                       CvSU Extension Services   activities           partnership in the
                                       Unit and concerned                             delivery of different
                                       colleges                                       projects/activities for
                                                                                      academic, research,
                                   ●   Provide technical                              extension, and
                                       assistance throughout the                      community development
                                       duration of the project
                                                                                  ●   Opportunity for faculty
                                   ●   Establish linkages with                        and students to gain
                                       government and non-                            actual experience in
                                       government agencies for                        community organizing,
                                       possible tie-ups                               conduct of training and
                                                                                      conduct of community
                                   ●   Help in sourcing out                           needs assessment and
                                       funds/donations/grants for                     impact studies of
                                       the projects                                   extension projects

                                   ●   Regularly monitor and
                                       evaluate the project
                                       activities in coordination
                                       with the CvSU Extension
                                       Unit















                                                            184]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[Table 3- 4  Academic Collaboration

                      NATURE OF            ROLE OF THE              ROLE OF            BENEFIT(S) FROM
                       LINKAGE              COLLEGE                PARTNER(S)            PARTNERSHIP
                    Cavite    State    CvSU shall:             CHED shall:           ●   Capacity building of
                    University   and                                                     faculty and staff.
                    Commission  on     a.  Provide open graduate  a.  Provide financial
                    Higher                programs in the K to    assistance and     ●   Improvement of the
                    Education             12 Transition Period    grants for the         University Faculty
                    (CHED)                as defined in CMO No.   development and/or     Profile.
                    (July 18, 2016)       4, s. 2016.             operation of
                                                                  programs of the    ●   Opportunity for
                    Academic    and    b.  Submit the liquidation   DHEI for the K to 12   research funding.

                    research              reports of all          Transition period as
                    collaboration         scholarship disbursals   outlined in Article VII,   ●   Upgrading of
                                          and expenses to         CMO No. 4, s. 2016.    facilities for
                                          CHED at the end of                             instruction, research,
                                          each academic year;   b.  Provide the required   and extension
                                          and                     funding for the        activities; and
                                                                  education of the
                                       c.  Maintain up-to-date    approved scholar/s   ●   Upgrading of library
                                          profiles and supply all   under the CHED K to   holdings.
                                          other information       12 Transition
                                          required on the CHED    Program, including
                                          Online Portal, when     but not limited to
                                          available               tuition fees, books,
                                                                  transportation,
                                                                  stipend and other
                                                                  privileges provided in
                                                                  CHED Memorandum
                                                                  Order (CMO) No. 3,
                                                                  s. of 2016,  and in
                                                                  accordance with
                                                                  pertinent laws, rules,
                                                                  and regulations; and

                                                               c.  Ensure the funding
                                                                  support for the
                                                                  faculty scholar’s
                                                                  education until full
                                                                  completion of the
                                                                  course program.

                    Cavite    State    CvSU shall:             DILG shall:           ●   Strengthened
                    University   and                                                     partnership with
                    Department   of    a.  Provide technical   a.  Provide necessary     DILG for academic,
                    Interior    and       expertise in the        data for various       research and
                    Local                 conduct of research on   DILG program,         community
                    Government            various DILG            projects and           development;
                    (DILG)   Region       programs, projects      activities (PPAs) that

                    IV-A                  and activities (PPAs)   could become       ●   Capacity building of
                    (CALABARZON)          such as Bottom-Up       possible of            CvSU faculty, staff,
                    (June 2016)           Budgeting (BUB),        engagement with        and students;
                                          Ugnayan ng Barangay     CvSU such as
                    Academic,             at mga Simbahan         Bottom-Up          ●   Opportunity for
                    research,             (UBAS) Disaster and     Budgeting (BUB),       academic, research
                    extension,   and      Risk Reduction          Ugnayan ng             and extension
                    community             Management (DRRM),      Barangay at mga        collaboration;
                    development           Manila Bay Clean-up     Simbahan (UBAS)
                    collaboration         and Rehabilitation      Disaster and Risk   ●   Promotion of CvSU
                                          Program (MBCRP),        Reduction              products and
                                          Salintubig, Watsan,     Management             services;
                                          etc.;                   (DRRM), Manila Bay
                                                                  Clean-Up and       ●   Training
                                       b.  Advocate to both       Rehabilitation         opportunities for
                                          undergraduate and       Program (MBCRP),
                                          graduate students

                                                            185]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[interested to study     Salintubig, Watsan,    faculty members and
                                          relevant DILG PPAs      etc.;                  student; and
                                          which are related to
                                          their courses.       b.  Provide necessary   ●   Scholarship for
                                                                  assistance to          undergraduate and
                                       c.  Share their knowledge   undergraduate and     graduate students.
                                          and products related    graduate student-
                                          to local governance to   interns who are
                                          LGRC and to             taking up courses
                                          extension facilities;   which have
                                          and                     relevance to various
                                                                  DILG PPAs;
                                       d.  Promote DILG IV-A by

                                          including the        c.  Provide either
                                          department’s website    administrative and/or
                                          address to the official   technical counterpart
                                          university website      to any other
                                          www.cvsu.edu.ph.        research study
                                                                  pertaining to local
                                                                  governance and
                                                                  development;

                                                               d.  Share knowledge
                                                                  products with CvSU;
                                                                  and

                                                               e.  Promote the
                                                                  university website by
                                                                  including at the
                                                                  Department’s
                                                                  website at
                                                                  www.calabarzon.dilg
                                                                  .gov.ph

                    Cavite    State    CvSU shall:             Impact Center shall:   ●   Opportunity for
                    University   and                                                     international
                    Impact   Centre,   a.  Engage in potential   a.  Engage in potential   academic and
                    University   of       exchange of faculty for   exchange of faculty   research
                    Toronto               joint teaching and      for joint teaching and   collaboration;
                    (December   11,       research programs;      research program;
                    2015)                 and                     and                ●   Strengthening
                                                                                         partnership and
                    Academic    and    b.  Encourage the       b.  Provide avenues for   furthering academic
                    research              enrolment of qualified   strengthening         excellence; and
                    collaboration         students in the other’s   partnership and
                                          academic programs.      furthering academic   ●   Promotion of
                                                                  excellence in          academic
                                                                  Canada and             excellence.
                                                                  Philippines.

                    Cavite    State     CvSU shall:            DAR shall:            ●   Strengthened
                    University   and                                                     partnership   with
                    DEPARTMENT         a.  Provide        the   a.  Conduct     and      DAR;
                    OF   AGRARIAN          CONSULTANT a copy       organizational  and

                    REFORM                 of  the  ARCESS  Sub-   enterprise   Needs   ●   Capacity  building of
                    (June 26, 2013)        Project proposal of the   Assessment  of  the   CvSU  faculty,  staff,
                                           CLIENT  that  shall be   ARBOs       and      and students; and
                    Technical              subjected  to  needs    immediate
                    consultancy            and         design      community  and  a   ●   Dissemination   of
                                           assessment;             Design  Assessment    university
                                                                   of   the   proposed   professional
                                       b.  Provide  the  funding   ARCCESS      sub-     services.
                                           requirement  for  the   project;
                                           Sub-project      ,
                                           amounting  to  One   b.  Choose  and  utilize
                                           Hundred   Thousand      an     appropriate
                                           Pesos (100,000.00)  to   Needs  Assessment

                                                            186]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[be  released in two (2)   Model in the conduct
                                           tranches; and           of  data  collection
                                                                   and  analysis.  The
                                       c.  Provide        the      organizational
                                           CONSULTANT      its     maturity assessment
                                           comments to the draft   (OMA)  tool  of  DAR
                                           report  referred  to  in   can  be  used  to
                                           item   no.5    the      assess   the   lead
                                           Obligations   of  the   ARBOS  and  other
                                           Consultant ,  not  later   ARBOS  involved in
                                           than  forty  eight  hour    the sub-project;
                                           (48)  after  receipt  of

                                           said report.        c.  Provide  a  list  of
                                                                   professional
                                                                   services     and
                                                                   common    service
                                                                   facility requirements
                                                                   with     technical
                                                                   specifications  and
                                                                   photos   of   the
                                                                   equipment;

                                                               d.  Submit   the  Final
                                                                   Report   of   the
                                                                   Organizational  and
                                                                   Enterprise   Needs
                                                                   Assessment   and
                                                                   Design  Assessment
                                                                   using  the  attached
                                                                   report format; and

                                                               e.  Submit   a   Draft
                                                                   Report not later than
                                                                   15  working  days
                                                                   after   receipt   of
                                                                   Notice  to  Proceed
                                                                   and the Final Report
                                                                   within   five   (5)
                                                                   working  days  upon
                                                                   receipt   of   the
                                                                   technical reviews  of
                                                                   DARPO.  A  printed
                                                                   copy of the Draft.

                    Cavite    State    CvSU shall:             FDKCC shall:           ●   Strengthened
                    University   and                                                     partnership   with
                    FIRST   DRAMA      a.  Award  Certificates  of   a.  Recommend   the   FDKCC   to   form
                    KOREAN  CAMP           Completion  to  the     student  participants   friendly  cooperative
                    CORPORATION            students  who  have     to the  program and   relationship  for  the
                    (January 3, 2013)      successfully            ensure  that  all  of   implementation   of
                                           completed     BPE       them  complied with   Bachelor of Physical
                    Academic               degree, trainings, and   immigration   and    Education  major  in
                    collaboration          short-term courses;     other  requirements   Golf  and  Leisure;
                                                                   for them  to study in   study tours; industry
                                       b.  Merit the students who   the Philippines;     immersion  trainings
                                           have   distinguished                          and      short-term
                                           themselves in this field   b.  Provide   facilities   courses; and

                                           of study;               and  other  logistical
                                                                   support  to  run  the   ●   Capacity building for
                                       c.  Offer   through  the    program in Korea;     faculty,  staff,  and
                                           concerned college and                         students.
                                           units  undergraduate   c.  Pay  the  University
                                           programs  specifically   an       amount
                                           BPE  major in Golf and   commensurate   to
                                           Leisure  and  through   the      program.
                                           International Program   Activity and duration
                                           Unit (IPU) study tours,   being applied for as

                                                            187]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[study    immersion      contained  in  the
                                           trainings  and  short   Implementing Rules
                                           term   courses   to     &  Regulation (IRR)
                                           Korean     students     pertaining  to  this
                                           sponsored  by  FDCC     MOA;
                                           and grant the diploma
                                           of  certificate  upon   d.  Provide   the
                                           completion   of  the    Professors   and
                                           program,  course  or    other     needed
                                           training;               personnel    from
                                                                   CvSU   with  pre-
                                       d.  Prepare  the  schedule   travel  expenses  to
                                           and       curricular    Korea,  board  and
                                           offerings   for   the   lodging  back  and
                                           program,  course,  or   forth airfare  to  and
                                           training in consultation   from   Manila,
                                           with the FDCC;          insurance,   and
                                                                   other   authorized
                                       e.  Select  and  provide    allowances in while
                                           competent  professors   in Korea;
                                           to handle the different
                                           professional courses;   e.  Source    out
                                                                   donations in Korea
                                       f.   Provide       the      for  IPU/CvSU.  This
                                           manpower,  staff,  and   donation  shall  be
                                           other  logical  support   utilized  to  improve
                                           for the program;        IPU/CvSU  services
                                                                   and  offerings  to
                                       g.  Through the Academic    Korean  and  other
                                           Affairs Unit, enroll the   foreign   students;
                                           Korean  students  in    and
                                           undergraduate
                                           programs,   English   f.   Ensure the safety of
                                           Proficiency and  short   the  professors and
                                           term   courses  and     other   authorized
                                           training   of   the     university personnel
                                           University;  pay  the   while in Korea.
                                           honorarium      of
                                           professors and  other
                                           personnel  who  shall
                                           be  involved  in  the
                                           program.  This  fund
                                           shall be sourced out of
                                           the fees collected from
                                           this program;

                                       h.  Ensure  the  safety  of
                                           the  foreign  students
                                           while  they  are  in  the
                                           University; and

                                       i.   Agree  that FDCC  can
                                           recommend   faculty
                                           members  externally if
                                           needed  to  enhance
                                           the   faculty  line-up
                                           competitiveness   as
                                           well  as  to  satisfy  the
                                           need from the student.

                    Cavite    State    CvSU shall:             MEGV shall:           ●   Financial support for
                    University   and                                                     the upgrading of
                    Ministry     of     a.  Offer graduate and   a.  Recommend the       facilities and faculty
                    Education,             undergraduate          student participants   enhancement;
                    Government   of        programs to Vanuatu    to the program and
                    Vanuatu (MEGV)         students sponsored     ensure that all of   ●   Opportunity for
                                           by VGFS and grant      them have complied     future research

                                                            188]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[diploma, degree, and   with immigration and   collaboration with
                    Academic               post-graduate          other requirements     MEGV; and
                    collaboration          certificates upon      to study in the
                    particularly   the     completion of the      Philippines;       ●   Strengthened
                    offering    and        program, course, or                           partnership with a
                    undertaking   of       training;           b.  Provide the facilities   foreign partner.
                    undergraduate                                 and other logistical
                    and  postgraduate   b.  Provide manpower,     support to run the
                    programs               staff and logistical   program in Vanuatu,
                                           support for the        if necessary;
                                           program undertaken

                                           by VGFS sponsored   c.  Pay the University
                                           students;              an amount
                                                                  commensurate to the
                                        c.  Provide academic      program/activity and
                                           reports of students’   duration being
                                           performance; and       applied for as
                                                                  contained in the
                                        d.  Designate an          implementing rules
                                           international          and regulations
                                           coordinator program,   (IRR) pertaining to
                                           who will take charge   the MOA; and
                                           of the VGFS.
                                                               d.  Provide payments to
                                                                  CvSU upon receiving
                                                                  the official invoices
                                                                  pertaining to tuition
                                                                  fees, other fees and
                                                                  allowances as
                                                                  required by CvSU for
                                                                  this VGFS
                                                                  sponsored student.

                    Cavite    State    CvSU shall:             Psyche       Guide     ●   Capacity building for
                    University   and                           Association,    Inc.      faculty,  staff,  and
                    Psyche    Guide                            shall:                    students.
                    Association, Inc.   a.  Provide manpower,   a.  Provide   Resource   ●   Strengthening
                                          staff and logistical    Person   for   the     partnership and
                                          support for the         seminars      and      furthering academic
                    Academic              program undertaken      trainings              excellence; and

                    collaboration         by PGAI sponsored    b.  Promote      and
                    particularly   the    seminar/training        Conduct the seminar/   ●   Promotion of
                    offering    and    b.  Promote and            training.              academic
                    undertaking   of      encourage the        c.  Award  certificates of   excellence.
                    psychology            participation of CvSU   participation   to   ●
                    related  trainings    students and faculty in   participants
                    and seminars          seminar/ training    d.  Pay the University an
                                                                  amount
                                                                  commensurate to the
                                                                  program. Activity and
                                                                  duration     being
                                                                  applied   for   as
                                                                  contained  in   the
                                                                  Implementing  Rules
                                                                  &  Regulation  (IRR)
                                                                  pertaining  to  this
                                                                  MOA;













                                                            189]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[Table 3- 5   On-the-Job Training Partners

                       NATURE OF           ROLE OF THE              ROLE OF            BENEFIT(S) FROM
                        LINKAGE              COLLEGE               PARTNER(S)            PARTNERSHIP
                       ON-THE-JOB       CvSU shall:            Company shall:        ●   Strengthened
                        TRAINING                                                         partnership for on-
                       PARTNERS         a.  provide quality    a.  believe that the      the-job training
                                            education to its      hands – on             development;
                                            students so that they   experiences of
                                            will become highly    female and male    ●   Capability
                                            capable and           students will greatly   enhancement of
                                            productive            improve their skills   students particularly
                                            individuals in their   and ultimately        in the media
                                            respective fields of   prepare them to the   industry;
                                            specialization;       real work
                                                                  environment;       ●   Opportunity for both

                                        b.  periodically monitor                         female and male
                                            the progress of the   b.  ensure that female   students undertake
                                            On- The –Job          and male student       worthwhile learning
                                            Training; and         trainees are given     experiences to
                                                                  equal opportunities    further the
                                        c.  make sure that        and protection;        development of their

                                            students observe the                         skills, competencies,
                                            policies, rules and   c.  closely supervise the   and attitudes toward
                                            regulation and the    trainees in the        work; and
                                            like of the           undertaking of their
                                            organization.         approved plan of   ●   Training of the
                                                                  work activities given   student concerned
                                                                  by their immediate     for a total duration
                                                                  supervisor; and        as stated in their
                                                                                         recommendation
                                                               d.  evaluate the          letter during regular
                                                                  performance of the     working days.
                                                                  trainee and submit
                                                                  the evaluation report
                                                                  to the University.





































                                                            190]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[3.8 BEST PRACTICES ADOPTED

                          CvSU’s best practices in strengthening its connections with the linkages:

                          1.  The leadership of the university is strongly supportive of establishing linkages

                               with  other  academic  and  research  institutions,  line  agencies,  local


                               government units, non-government organizations, foreign counterparts, and

                               the  industry  sector.  The  university  provides  an  enabling  mechanism  to

                               facilitate linkage activities of faculty and staff.

                          2.  The university has  an  International and  Local  Collaboration and  Linkages

                               Office by virtue of BOR Resolution No. 8, series of 2019  that is concerned


                               with all  the external linkages of the university particularly those covered by

                               Memorandum  of  Agreement  (MOA)  or  Memorandum  of  Understanding

                               (MOU).  The  ILCLO  keeps  an  updated  record  of  project  activities  and

                               periodically submits reports to the President on the status of each project.

                          3.  CvSU  faculty  and  staff  are  encouraged  to  engage  in  linkage  activities

                               particularly  with  their  academic  and  research  counterparts.  Funds  are

                               provided to enable them to attend training, conferences, research symposia


                               and seminars to facilitate their linkage activities.

                          4.  The  university encourages multidisciplinary  research  among  two  or  more

                               disciplines  particularly  those  with  counterparts from  other  academic  and

                               research institutions (both foreign and local).  Likewise, the university also

                               promotes collaborative research with the industry.


                          5.  There is effective lateral communication within the university. The sharing of

                               information can foster a collaborative atmosphere within the university and

                               between the university and outside community.

                          6.  The  university employs  the  service of a  legal  consultant  who  is  actively

                               involved in formulation and guidance on preparation or review of documents

                               such  as  Memorandum  of  Agreement  (MOA)  or  Memorandum  of

                               Understanding  (MOU).  Collaboration  agreements  and  proposals  are


                                                            191]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[submitted   to   the    legal   consultant   who    provides   appropriate

                               amendments/corrections to  ensure that  relevant  terms  are  laid  down  for

                               execution.

                          7.  The university involves the various  stakeholders during strategic  planning


                               workshops and other relevant university functions. This practice will enable

                               the stakeholders to identify the needs of the university and inspire them to

                               forge a meaningful and sustainable collaboration in enhancing the quality of

                               instruction, research, and extension functions of the university.

                          8.  The graduates of the University are the best spokesperson or ambassadors


                               of the University. As such, strong ties had been kept by the University with its

                               thousands of graduates many  of which had  occupied key positions in the

                               workplace. These links with the alumni  were and are instrumental in getting

                               employment for a lot of graduates and in establishing a  global network that

                               has the potential of further helping CvSU widen its international exposure.

                          9.  Prospective partners are carefully evaluated for their roles and relevance to

                               the University’s inherent functions of instruction, research, and extension.


                          10.  Existing  partnerships are  regularly monitored and  evaluated  to  determine

                               status, progress, and address immediate concerns. Scheduled visits to the

                               linkage establishments are also being done.

                          11.  Linkage  and  networking  activities  have  been  made  transparent  to  the

                               members of the academic community.


                          12.  The university maintains a harmonious relationship with its partners through

                               recognizing their invaluable contribution in being part of the on-the-job training

                               of students. This practice is expected to deliver more linkages in the future.

                          13.  At present, the university conducts orientation for on-the-job training so as to

                               prepare students on the expectations of the establishments where they will be

                               deployed. The university is making sure that students are ready to embrace





                                                            192]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[the industry. As a result, students are receiving recognition from their training

                               area for being excellent in their job performance.

                          14.  The support that the University gives to its linkage establishments has helped

                               in  strengthening their connections and  in  expanding more  linkages in  the


                               future.

                          15.  Key personnel of the linkage establishments are invited to serve as resource

                               speakers during culminating activities, and other events of the college.



































































                                                            193]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[2018 CAS Benchmarking with St. Louis University Baguio Psychology Department






























                      BS Psychology students undergoing a workshop on student facilitation and mental
                     health crisis response under the supervision of Ms. Gilian Joan Hernandez, RGC, the
                                               University Guidance Counselor








                                                            194]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[Psyche Guide Inc., one of the linkage institutions of BS Psychology program,
                    conducting a seminar-workshop entitled “Gearing Up for Psychological First Aid: Basic
                                    Steps in Helping People with Mental Health Problem”











                                                            195]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[From left, Jezreel Del Espiritu Santo, Mary Joyce Talamante, Mary Jane Amparo, and
                   Armi Grace Desingaño, psychology instructors, attending the seminar-workshop entitled
                     “The Legacy of Fr. Bulatao: Working with the Unconscious, Extrasensory Perception,
                                                    and Hyperempathy”













                                                            196]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[The department kept strong ties with its graduates that are instrumental in establishing
                     linkages. Mr. Ron Gabriel A. Peji, a BS Psychology graduate batch 2018, sharing his
                       insights about mental health, during the annual general assembly of psychology
                                                      students in 2019





























                    CAS-DSSH's forum titled "No to Drug Addiction, Stop Extrajudicial Killings: A Righteous
                      and Moral Legacy to Filipino Youth" with BS Psychology 2007 graduate Mr. Marvin
                                                        Ambion, RPm


                                                            197]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[198]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[Memorandum of



                       Understanding (MOU) /




                                  Memorandum of



                                Agreement (MOA)






































































                                                            199]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[200]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[201]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[202]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[203]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[204]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[205]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[206]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[207]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[208]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[209]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[210]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[211]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[212]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[213]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[214]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[215]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[216]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[217]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[218]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[219]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[220]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[221]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[222]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[223]]></page></pages></Search>