<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="115"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[2. EXTENSION

               2. INTRODUCTION ……………………………………………………………                                         4


                  2.1    Well-Defined Objectives…………………………………………….                                7



                  2.2    Adequate and Relevant Projects/Activities to Achieve Objectives .        65


                         2.2.1 Technical Service Consultancy ……………………………..                        66



                         2.2.2 Technology Dissemination ……………………………….....                         67



                  2.3    Systematic and Effective Procedures ……………………….....                       75


                  2.4    Reasonable Budget …………………………………………………                                    84



                  2.5    Provision of Materials and other Resources ……………………                      89


                  2.6    Participation  of  Significant  Number  of  Faculty  /  Staff/  Students  /
                         Community in Major Projects/Activities ……………                             91



                  2.7    Awards of Distinction/Achievement and Grants of Bs Psychology.           97



                  2.8    Best Practices Adopted …………………………………………..                                102


                         2.8.1 Conduct of Income Generating Activities …………………….                  102


                         2.8.2 Continuous Support of Extension Staff, Faculty and Students        102



                         2.8.3 Administrative Support …………………………...………….                          103



                         2.8.4 Active Involvement of Extension Linkages ………………….                  103














                                                            1]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[LIST OF TABLES

               Table 2.1  Extension Activities from 2013-2020 of the BS Psychology Program        59

                Table      Budgetary allocation for the conduct of University extension projects

                2.2        and actual expenditures for the year 2013 to 2017 (in thousand pesos)

                           ……………………………………………………..                                                 84



                Table      Budgetary allocation for the conduct of college extension activities

                2.3        from 2013 to 2019………………………………………...                                    86


                Table      List of Agency/Unit/Office and Participants that provide support and

                2.4        assistance  in  the  implementation  of  extension  programs  of  the

                           department ……………………………………………………..                                      89

                Table      List of university extension linkages ……………………………...                   91

                2.5

                Table      DSSH  BS  Psychology  extension  projects  and  activities  from

                2.6        2013-2020 ……………………………………………………………                                      92




































                                                            2]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[LIST OF FIGURES



                   Figure 2.1   General  process  flow  of  research  and  extension  program   75
                              implementation ………………………………………………





























































                                                            3]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[2 EXTENSION


               INTRODUCTION


                       Republic  Act  No.  8468  mandates  CvSU  to  provide  an  advanced  introduction  and

               professional  training  in  agriculture,  science  and  technology,  education,  and  other  fields,

               undertake  research  and  extension  services,  and  provide  progressive  leadership  in  these

               areas.  Likewise,  the  university’s  mission  of  providing  excellent,  equitable  and  relevant


               educational opportunities in the arts, science and technology through quality instruction and

               responsive  research  and  development  activities  has  continuously  inspired  people  in  the

               academe to pursue extension activities.


                       As it seeks to produce professional, skilled and morally upright individuals for global

               competitiveness, CvSU maintains to take its root for being relevant to the community it is


               bound  to  serve.  Thus,  the  university  extension  agenda  was  established  to  the  University

               level, where each unit takes its ground.


                       The College of Arts and Sciences sets its extension activities with inputs from faculty,

               staff, students, LGU, NGO/NGA, alumni, and other stakeholders. It involves the application


               of the existing and new knowledge and technology to improve the quality of life of the people

               in  the  community.  A  community  model  of  development  inspires  CAS  to  conceptualize

               different extension activities to empower people or residents of nearby communities.


                       The College of Arts and Sciences supports the university mission that is to provide


               excellent,  equitable,  and  relevant  educational  opportunities  through  quality  instruction  and

               responsive research and development activities.


                                   st
                       Indang is a 1  class municipality composed of 36 barangays; 12 urban and 24 rurals;
               and with a population of 65,599 as per 2015 census.




                                                            4]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Predominant, Indang remains rural because the municipal area is primarily devoted

               to  agriculture.  In fact,  approximately  80% of  7,176.38  hectares  are  predominantly  planted


               with  various  types  of  crops  like  coconut,  banana,  coffee,  fruit  trees,  and  pineapple,  while

               there are small portions of rice, root crops, vegetables, and corn.


                       Indang  caters  to  different  levels  of  education.  Both  public  and  private  schools

               welcome  enrollees  from  different  walks  of  life.  Cavite  State  University  is  the  only  tertiary


               institution  in  the  municipality.  The  prestigious  institution  offers  professional  and  special

               education for special purposes.


                       The  Municipal  Social  Welfare  and  Development  Office  provides  assistance  to  the

               needy and disadvantaged families through different programs like SEA K Program, practical


               skills training and development and AID to Individual in Crisis Institution. In Addition, only 13

               barangays have existing health centers.


                       With the  present  needs  of the municipality, the  Extension  services  of Cavite  State


               University,  College  of  Arts  and  Sciences  came  up  with  a  program  to  empower  the

               community. These would include projects concerning community welfare and development,

               health and wellness, literacy projects, and agriculture and environmental awareness.


                       Barangay  Daine  is  one  of  the  36  barangays  in  the  municipality  of  Indang.  The

               barangay  is  in  a  strategic  position  to  be  of  service  to  the  general  development  of  the

               municipality. Given the proper and prompt assistance to the needs of the barangay and its

               people  will  put  the  barangay  in  a  competitive  position  to  prove  itself  a  potent  partner  in

               community development. Based on the Needs Assessment, most of the residents showed


               interest in generating more income. This was followed by the group who were interested in

               learning technologies that may give them extra income. It could be surmised that one of the






                                                            5]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[major causes of stress and anxiety by the residents are related to finances. (Agdalpen, et al,

               2011)


                       The CvSU- College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) extension unit has been targeting

               Barangay  Daine  in  Indang,  Cavite  as  a  focal  point  of  its  services  to  the  community.

               Originally,  they  were  serving  Barangay  Daine  I  but  later  moved  to  Indang  Habitat

               Gangneung  Pine  Village  (IHGPV)  in  Barangay  Daine  II  since  majority  are  actively


               participating due to homogeneity of the population and interests were sustained that make it

               effective in formulating varied programs of the different departments of the College of Arts

               and Sciences. (Nahilat, 2015) Diane II is a barangay in the municipality of Indang, in the

               province  of  Cavite.  Its  population  as  determined  by  the  2015  Census  was  2,322.  This

               represented 3.54% of the total population of Indang. IHGPV in Daine II has served since


               2011.

                       Department of Social Sciences and Humanities through the extension project of the

               BS  Psychology  Program  aims to  empower  communities  through  the  PASYA  MO,  BUHAY

               MO  A  Psychological  Approach  towards  Values  Reorientation,  Self-empowerment  and


               Couple-empowerment  through  Community  Adoption  Services:  KABARANGAY  AT

               KAESKWELA  for  INDANG  HABITAT  GANGNEUNG  PINE  VILLAGE.  Moreover,  for  wider

               scope of extending and continuing the assistance, the extension services unit of the college

               adopted a nearby municipality and barangay, Barangay Asis 1 and 3 Mendez, Cavite.


                       To  effectively  perform  its  research  and  extension  (R&E)  functions  and  to  guide  its


               directions in the next five years, CAS proposed a comprehensive agenda for research and

               extension sustainability dubbed simply as CAS CARES. CAS CARES is an enhancement of

               the College’s R&E programs in the previous years. It is aligned to the University’s Research,







                                                            6]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Development,  and  Extension  Agenda  and  Programs  as  well  as  to  national,  even

               international, development goals and thrusts.


               2.1 WELL-DEFINED OBJECTIVES


                       The Extension Services perform the third major function of Cavite State University. It

               links  this  educational  institution  with  the  community  through  the  conduct  of  non-formal

               education and training, technology demonstration and technology transfers to rural men and


               women, farmers, pupils, out-of-school youth, and other community development activities.


                       Extension  programs  are  geared  to  carry  out  the  University’s  goal  of  assisting  the

               target clients in their struggle for improving their quality of life. Initial efforts were made at the

               university  level  to  enhance  and  strengthen  its  services  through  effective  and  efficient

               implementation.  Monitoring  and  evaluation,  resource  generation,  linkages  as  well  as


               coordination of various activities are part of the extension program.

               Goal of the University Extension Services


                       The Extension Services of Cavite State University (CvSU) shall be geared towards


               the improvement of the lives of the community especially those that belong to economically

               and socially disadvantaged sectors through the conduct of relevant education and training;

               farm  and  business  advisory  activities;  demonstration  projects;  and  information,

               communication and technology services.


               Objectives of the University Extension Services


                       The University shall provide excellent and socially responsive extension services to

               its target clientele.


                       Specifically, it aims to:






                                                            7]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[1. Conduct and/or coordinate relevant training programs as well as appropriate, efficient and

               sustainable interdisciplinary extension programs;


               2. Promote community and social enterprises;


               3. Coordinate and monitor the extension activities of various colleges and branch campuses

               of the University;


               4.  Establish linkages with government and private agencies engaged in extension and


               development;


               5. Coordinate with the Office of the Vice President for Resource Generation and Production

               (OVPRGP) in promoting agricultural and other potential income generating projects; and


               6. Promote gender-responsive extension programs and activities.


               Goal of the College of Arts and Sciences Extension Unit


                       A  unified,  coordinated,  participatory,  responsive,  and  relevant  extension  and


                   development programs within the university and its service area.


               Objectives of the CAS-Extension Program


                       The extension services of the College of Arts and Sciences aims to improve quality


                   of life through proper health management, literacy programs and agricultural projects in

                   the community.

















                                                            8]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Community Adoption Services: Kabarangay at Kaeskwela for Indang

               Habitat Gangneung Pine Village (CAS:KK for IHGPV)

                       A three-year extension program towards a peaceful, productive and aesthetic IHGPV

               community, where home partners possess functional knowledge, skills and attitude to effect


               change in their own lives benefiting not only to themselves but to the whole community.


               Goal of Community Adoption Services: Kabarangay At Kaeskwela For Indang Habitat

               Gangneung Pine Village (CAS: KK FOR IHGPV)


                       In general, it is expected that this extension program will strengthen the educational

               delivery systems between and among interested residents of IHGPV, Daine 2.


               Objectives of CAS: KK for IHGPV


                       The program aims to enhance positive value reorientation that will bring about:


                       1. increased youth’s competence level in basic Math, Language, Arts and


                       environmental concern;

                       2. increased family’s livelihood opportunities for increased family income;


                       3. increase in local governance’s level of leadership in community


                       development activities; and

                       4. elevation of the client system from recipients to program partners in

                       community development.














                                                            9]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Objectives of the “PASYA MO, BUHAY MO” Program (Psychology extension

               program in IHGPV)


                       Generally,  PASYA  MO,  BUHAY  MO  Project  under  CAS:  KK  for  IHGPV  aims  to


               empower the self, women and couples of IHGPV and enhance values reorientation through

               the Psychological Approach.

                       Specifically, the objectives of the project are the following:

               1. discuss how couple differences may use in Increasing couple power towards participation

               in IHGPV activities for community development; and


               2. appreciate varied roles of husband and wife in building strong family and community ties.



                       Meanwhile, CAS CARES is an enhancement of the College’s R&E programs in the

               previous years. A series of workshops was conducted to study the best practices in R&E as

               well  as  the  completed,  on-going,  and  proposed  R&E  projects  and  activities  of  the  four

               departments of CAS. Likewise, the University’s R&E agenda and programs were presented

               and  considered  in  crafting  this  proposed  agenda  of  the  College.  It  is  aligned  to  the


               University’s  Research,  Development,  and  Extension  Agenda  and  Programs  as  well  as  to

               national, even international, development goals and thrusts.

                    The three banner programs under CAS CARES are:


                    1. CAS HELPS: Community Adoption Services: Health and Wellness, Environment and


               Biodiversity, Learning Programs, and Societal Development

                    2. CAS Bee: Community Adoption and Strengthening of the CvSU Bee Program


                    3. CAS Coffee: Culture, Art, and Science of Philippine Coffee










                                                           10]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[For CAS HELPS, there are four subprograms – BIO, DLMC, DPS, and SOCSCI –

               representing the four departments within the College.


               Goals of CAS CARES


                    This comprehensive agenda for research and extension sustainability aims to:


                    1. provide a framework for the relevance and sustainability of research and extension in


                   the fields of arts, sciences, and technology

                    2. enhance capabilities of faculty members, students, and staff through engagement in

                   R and E activities


                    3.  respond to the needs and requests of various stakeholders by extending technical


                   assistance and consultancy services

                    4. strengthen local and international R and E collaborations and linkages


                    5. improve the quality of lives of stakeholders


               Program Descriptions and Objectives


                    The descriptions and objectives of each program are as follows:


                    CAS  HELPS  stands  for  Community  Adoption  and  Services:  Health  and  Wellness,

               Environment and Biodiversity, Learning Programs, and Societal Development. This banner

               program focuses mainly on extension projects which are either research/technology-driven

               or  needs/demand-driven.  In  some  cases,  extension  activities  also  respond  to  various

               requests  from  stakeholders.  HELPS  represents  the  local  and  international  research  and


               development thrusts and goals to which these extension projects are aligned.








                                                           11]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Social Organization through Comprehensive Services and Community Intervention

               (SOCSCI)


                    SOCSCI  is  a  sub-program  for  research  and  extension  of  the  Department  of  Social


               Sciences  and  Humanities.  It  aims  to  analyze  societal  problems  scientifically  and  provide

               comprehensive  community  services  in  promoting  socio-political  and  psycho-cultural

               development; to improve the quality of life of intended partners through sustainable research

               and  extension  projects;  to  strengthen  external  linkages;  and  to  advocate  gender  and


               development.

                   Specifically, it aims to:


                    1. conduct collaborative researches in the fields of Political Science, Psychology, and

                   Social Work;


                    2.  conduct relevant and timely extension activities for target clients with emphasis on

                   socio-political and psycho-cultural aspects of societal development; and


                    3.  respond  to  the  requests  of  various  government  and  non-government  agencies


                   needing  faculty  expertise  in  Social  Sciences  and  Humanities  by  providing  technical

                   assistance and consultancy services.


                   The successfulness and positive feedback from the extension program of BS Psychology

               in Indang Habitat Gangneung Pine Village in Barangay Daine 2, Indang, Cavite has brought

               about the  commencement  of  another  extension project  on  the  college  in  Mendez,  Cavite:


               CAS  CARES,  CAS  HELPS  Community  Adoption  Services:  Health  and  wellness,

               Environment  and  Biodiversity,  Learning  Programs  and  Societal  Development  which  is

               participated by the Department of Social Science and Humanities with the vision of SOCSCI:

               Social Organization Through Comprehensive Services and Community Intervention.





                                                           12]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Thus, the Extension project of the BS Psychology program continues to give assistance

               in other places in Cavite, particularly in Brgy Asis 1 and 3 Mendez, Cavite. The project is

               PSYCHOSOCIAL  SERVICES  YEARNING  TOWARDS  COMMUNITY  HEALTH  AND

               WELLNESS (PSYCH) that will focus on VALUES ORIENTATION AND RE-ORIENTATION

               of the community.

               Objectives of PSYCH


                       Generally, the program aims to develop moral functioning through values formation

               and reorientation activities.

                       Specifically, the extension program intends:

               1.      To inculcate Filipino values

               2.      To form new values based on the discussed universal values

               3.      To perform newly formed values

               4.      To identify different values that has been repressed

               5.      To reinvigorate and reorient values that was found to be repressed

               6.      To perform the values reoriented

                    Among  the  above-mentioned  objectives  of  the  program,  this  also  prepares  BS

               Psychology  students to undertake research  and  development  and  enhance their  ability to


               provide  appropriate  technical  assistance  and  skills  development  to  the  beneficiaries  they

               wish to assist.



















                                                           13]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Home Visitation and needs assessment conducted by the BS Psychology instructors in

               Indang Habitat Gangneung Pine Village in Brgy Daine 2, Indang, Cavite














                                                           14]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Mary  Joyce  Eyaya,  Psychology  Extension  Coordinator  spearheaded  the  needs


               assessment together with Kristine Grace Garcia, Mary Jane Amparo, Ana Ruth Andalajao,

               Psychology faculty members.


               November 15, 2013- Social Sciences volunteer faculty members went on an initial visit for a

               needs assessment and simple familiarizing activity in the area.They were introduced to the


               community leaders. House to house interviews were done for the needs assessment. CAS

               faculty engaged in a conversation with the local resident. The following are the initial results

               of the interview:


                   1.  Residents are available only on weekends. Although Saturday mornings are


                       reserved for the regular market day.

                   2.  Most married females are plain housewives and they are looking for business

                       opportunities as another source of income for their family.






                                                           15]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[3.  residents are engaged in Kaong planting and utilizing the plant and its fruit in

                       different ways.

                   4.  IHGPV residents lead a simple but peaceful life but helpful training or seminars on


                       child rearing would be of help.


               After the initial visit, CAS Extension started working on their timeline and proposal.







































               The stakeholders shared their dreams and aspirations towards the CASKK for IHGPV. Dr.

               Jun Lapitan from iHome Indang, the principal from Daine Western Institute, Ms. Julit Ilagan

               from Kiwanis International Treasures of Indang, and Dr. Evelyn Singson, CAS Dean signed


               the Memorandum of Agreement







                                                           16]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Barangay visitation spearheaded by Dean Bettina Joyce P. Ilagan, PhD. together with

                                          faculties of different department of CAS




                                                           17]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Barangay Asis Mendez officials with Psychology Instructors and students












                                                           18]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Consultative Meeting for Mendez Extension Program together with

                                                     Mayor Eric Vida





                                                           19]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[The first activity was Si ako, Si Ikaw, Iba Ma’y Pinag Isa (Gender Differences). That activity

               is about the gender differences of husband and wife in terms of physical, mental, emotional

               aspect of the individual and how these differences can empower one another and eventually


               the community of IHGPV. Due to the success of the activity, the participants requested for a

               repeat performance. They wanted their spouses, who were at work that time, to attend.






                                                           20]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[21]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[22]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[23]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[OPEN FORUM: The participants lively asked different questions about the problems they

               have encountered in their respective families.



































                                                           24]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[25]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[26]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[27]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[28]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[29]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[This 3-year Extension program is

               under the guidance of the Office of the CAS Dean, Dr. Lynn G. Penales. In the photo above,

               Mary Jane Amparo (Psychology Instructor), Joy Babaan (Psychology Program Coordinator,

               the speaker, and Dr. Cecille Lapitan (CAS Extension Coordinator)







                                                           30]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[Host: MARY JANE AMPARO,                     PRAYER: Shally Mae Villa, 4thyr Psychology


               Psychology Instructor                       student





































                                                           31]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[32]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[.

























               Mr. Alan B. Lee as resource speaker in Kahinaa’y Lakas, Kabigua’y Tagumpay, Ikaw at

               Ako Mggkaagapay (Art of Conjugal Harmony: Handling Marital Conflicts make it easy





























                 Ms. Ana Ruth Andalajao together with BS Psychology students serving as coordinator during

                                                  the Extension activity





                                                           33]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[BS Psychology students served as coordinator for the activity





































                                                           34]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[The participants listened attentively to the speaker.



















































                 Dr. Cecilia Banaag, Psychology professor served as the speaker about “the Choice to do

                                                      What is Right”











                                                           35]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[Ernecita C. Corpuz as a resource speaker on the seminar, “The Choice to Make a

                                                       Difference”








                                                           36]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[The resource speaker from Avon on the seminar,





























                                          “The Choice to Take Care of Yourself”




                                                           37]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Psychology Instructors with the speaker, Dr. Bernadette Sapinoso.































                                                  The women of IHGPV




                                                           38]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[Dr. Banaag giving her remarks as a guest speaker































                                       Awarding of certificate to the guest speaker




                                                           39]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[December 2, 2017 Community Visit at Asis Mendez Cavite by DSSH Faculty Members

                                             during their Barangay Assembly








































                                                           40]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[November 17, 2017 Community Visit and GAD Orientation


























                               GAD Orientation facilitated by GAD Advocate Merlie Nahilat








                                                           41]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[The speaker, Mr. Carlo Malaunan, as he conducts the seminar about Values


               Formation to the youth of Mendez, Cavite










                                                           42]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[Dr. Paul Hilario as resource speaker on The Choice to Grow: Values Reorientation










                                                           43]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[Mr. Gadon as resource speaker during the Drug Prevention Seminar with the pupils of

                          Constancio E. Aure Sr. National High School in Brgy Asis, Mendez, Cavite
















                                                           44]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[With Taal volcano’s eruption last January 2020, the Psychology program’s extension

                     unit under the Department of Social Sciences and Humanities of the College of Arts

                     and  Sciences  rendered  psychological  first  aid  to  displaced  residents  of  Batangas.

                     Proper  coordination  with  the  Municipal  Social  Welfare  and  Development  offices  of


                     Mendez, Alfonso, Indang, Bailen, and Magallanes were made to ensure a smooth and

                     organized delivery of PFA services.






























                       Initial Meeting with the Guidance Counselors and Psychology Instructors about The

                                           Psychological First Aid they will conduct.



















                                                           45]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[Visited several municipalities for coordination about the PFA



















                                                           46]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[In trying to keep up with this time of improved technology, internet accessibility and due

                     to  physical  distance,  a  group  chat  thru  Facebook  Messenger  was  created  to  stay

                     connected  with  the  PFA  volunteers  who  attended  the  training.  This  way  of


                     communication proved effective during brainstorming and organizing the volunteers in

                     groups, designations, and assigned areas.














                                                           47]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Psychology  instructors  through  the  joint  efforts  of  DSSH  and  other  CAS  departments
               organized a Psychological First Aid Training with Dr. Cecilia Banaag and Dr. Paulito Hilario
               as  speakers/trainors.  The  first  training  was  attended  by  CVSU  students,  graduate  school

               students, as well as alumni. The second training was participated by both teaching and

               non-teaching      staff     of      CVSU       main       and      satellite    campuses.

























































                                                           48]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[Consistent  follow  ups  were  done  with  the  different  MSWD  coordinators  in  the  different

               evacuation centers in Indang, Mendez, and Alfonso to ensure effectiveness of the PFA as


               well as if there are needs arising which requires swift action.





























































                                                           49]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[Aside from PFA, donations and repacking of goods were also done by the group of

                     instructors and volunteers to help the MSWD in assisting the Taal evacuees.
































































                                                           50]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[Just as the Cavitenos were about to recover from the effects of the Taal volcano eruption,

               the spread of COVID-19 rose to the shock of the Filipino people as well as the whole world

               and eventually, a pandemic happened. Some areas in the Philippines with concentration in

               Luzon  were  placed  on  Enhanced  Community  Quarantine  and  then  was  escalated  to


               becoming  Extreme  Enhanced  Community  Quarantine  because  of  the  rapid  spread  of  the

               virus.  People  were  advised  to  stay  at  home  and  only  one  member  of  the  family  with  a

               quarantine pass was allowed to go out to buy necessities. Stores and establishments were

               closed, jobs  were  put  on  hold,  all  forms  of  gatherings  were  prohibited  including  important

               events such as graduation, and church related activities. Fear and worry engulfed the people


               and while some were able to cope, others were not. Instructors of the Psychology Program

               of  the  Department  of  Social  Sciences  and  Humanities  under  the  College  of  Arts  and

               Sciences made use of their skills and knowledge in conducting Psychological First Aid and

               Psychosocial  Support  in  the  hope  of  reaching  out  to  individuals,  especially  students  and

               other stakeholders who were feeling overwhelmed and anxious because of the situation. The


               effort proved to be effective and useful considering the number of turn-out.






























                                                           51]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[52]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[As face to face interaction is prohibited, online PFA/PSS was fully utilized to cater

               stakeholders. The internet proved useful and convenient in reaching out to clients even for


               the posting of promotional posters for such.





























































                                                           53]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[With the support and encouragement of Dr. Bettina Joyce P. Ilagan, Dean of the College of

               Arts  and  Sciences,  the  Psychology  Program  Extension  unit  conducted  an  online

               “CASmustahan” which also served as a semi-webinar with question and answer in promoting

               mental  health  and  teaching  students,  colleagues  and  other  stakeholders  in  mental  and


               emotional self-care during the time of the COVID-19 pandemic. The July 1 activity,  which

               was  held  through  the  online  platform  Zoom  and  was  broadcasted  live  through  Facebook,

               lasted for two (2) hours with eight thousand three hundred views (8300) and one hundred

               thirty two(132) shares.



































               The  PFA/PSS  is  still  on-going  and  continuous  monitoring  is  being  done  by  involved

               Psychology  instructors  to  ensure  that  clients  are  able  to  manage  and  cope  well  with  the


               pandemic. Further, the July 1 semi-webinar was properly evaluated by a number of willing

               viewers through Google Form to ensure service improvement.




                                                           54]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[The CoronaVirus Pandemic has become a major global problem that affects people’s

               activities,  relationship,  and  financial,  emotional, and  physical  condition. More  people  need

               support  in  whatever  means  whether  psychological  first  aid,  prayers,  advice  etc.  The

               extension  program  of  CVSU-CAS-DSSH  responded  and  reached-out  through  Social


               Distancing, Quarantine Program and other ordinances restricted physical contact and limited

               the program that the extension services can offer. But those factors instead of obstructing

               the  plans,  it  became  a  means  to  repackage  the  extension  activities  in  a  flexible  way.  On

               October  5,  2020,  a  Department  Meeting  was  held  for  the  purpose  of  planning  for  the

               extension  activities  for  the  month  of  October.  Then  two  days  after,  October  7,  2020,  a

               Consultative Meeting was held at Barangay Asis 1 and 3, Mendez, Cavite. It was agreed to

               have the webinar on Mental Health Awareness: October 24, 2020, Saturday at 9:00 AM. Last


               October 24, 2020 a Webinar on Mental Health was held via Facebook live. It was mainly for

               the Barangay Officials and Front liners and the community of Barangay Asis 1 and

               3    but invitation was extended to other communities and individuals because of the


               relevance of the topic.





















                                              DSSH Meeting Via Google Meet








                                                           55]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[Consultative Meeting at Barangay Asis 1 and 3




                                                           56]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[The resource speaker of the Webinar on Mental Health Awareness


                                        MISS MA. ALODIA CUENO-MERCADO, RPsy











                                                           57]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[After the Consultative Meeting on Barangay Asis 1 and 3 on Oct 7, 2020, the Faculty of

               CAS-DSSH  donated  five  (5)  boxes  of  bond  papers  at  Asis  Elementary  School.  This  is  to


               assist the Public school teachers who are printing modules for their pupils.





























































                                                           58]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[Table 2.1. Extension activities from 2013-2020 of the BS Psychology Program



                 Title of the Activity   Date       Faculty            Clientele         Nature of

                                                    Involved           /Beneficiary      Involvement

                 2013


                 CAS: KK for IHGPV     December     Mary Joyce         IHGPV Home        Facilitator,

                 MOU SIGNING           14, 2013     Eyaya              Partners          Support Staff

                 2014


                 Year 1 Si Ako, Si     February     Mary Joyce         IHGPV Home        Coordinator,

                 Ikaw: Iba ma’y        8, 2014      Eyaya              Partners          Facilitator,


                 Pinag-isa             and          Mary Jane                            Support Staff

                 Gender Differences    February     amparo

                                       25, 2014     Louziela

                                                    Masana

                                                    Imelda Filart

                                                    Ana Ruth

                                                    Andalajao


                 Values Reorientation  August 10,  Mary Joyce          IHGPV Home        Speaker,

                 Part 1. “The Choice   2014         Eyaya              Partners          Coordinator,

                 to Grow”                           Czherie Fei                          Facilitator,

                 Ako sa Pangarap                    Ledesma                              Support Staff


                 kong Buhay                         Cecilia Banaag








                                                           59]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[Values Reorientation  October 5,   Mary Joyce         IHGPV Home        Coordinator,Su

                 Part 2. “The Choice   2014         Eyaya              Partners          pport Staff

                 to Give”                           Mary Jane

                                                    Amparo


                 Values Reorientation  October      Maty Joyce         IHGPV Home        Coordinator,Su

                 Part 3. “The Choice   12, 2014     Eyaya              Partners          pport Staff

                 to Listen”                         Joy Babaan

                                                    Mary Jane

                                                    Amparo


                 2015


                 Year 2: “Art of       February     Mary Joyce         IHGPV Home        Coordinator,Su

                 Conjugal Harmony:     15, 2015     Eyaya              Partners          pport Staff

                 Marital Conflicts                  Mary Jane

                 Make it Easy...                    Amparo


                 Kahinaa’y Lakas,                   Ana Ruth

                 Kabigua’y                          Andalajao

                 Tagumpay, Ikaw at

                 Ako Magkaagapay”


                 Values Reorientation  February     Mary Joyce         IHGPV Home        Coordinator,Su

                 Part 4 SSS            22, 2015     Eyaya              Partners          pport Staff

                 PAGIBIG:                           Mary Jane

                 Sustaining,                        Amparo

                 Strengthening and                  Joy Babaan





                                                           60]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[Satisfying one’s

                 Relationship


                 Values Reorientation  March 1,     Mary Joyce         IHGPV Home        Coordinator,Su

                 Part 5: “The Choice   2015         Eyaya              Partners          pport Staff

                 to Make a                          Mary Jane

                 Difference: She                    Amparo

                 says, He says, We                  Ana Ruth


                 say”                               Andalajao


                 Values Reorientation  Sept. 13,    Mary Joyce         IHGPV Home        Coordinator,

                 Part 6 “The Choice    2015         Eyaya              Partners          Facilitator,

                 To Take Care of                    Josephine                            Support Staff


                 Yourself”                          Manapsal
                                                    Mary Jane


                                                    Amparo

                                                    Ma. Glenda

                                                    Torreda

                                                    Alyssa Eseque

                                                    John Christian


                                                    Paolo Belen

                                                    Armi Grace

                                                    Desingano

                                                    Leonido Orsal

                                                    Jr.







                                                           61]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[Renato

                                                    Agdalpen

                                                    Mike Oliver

                                                    Gimao


                 “Project Alalay”: Ang   October,   CAS and CON        IHGPV Home        Coordinator,

                 malusog na NANAY,     25, 2015     faculty            Partners          Facilitator,

                 sa Tahana’y                        members                              Support Staff


                 Matagumpay na

                 Kaagapay

                 2016


                 Year 3: Anak na       February     Mary Joyce         IHGPV Home        Coordinator,Su

                 Biyaya Aalagaan,      28, 2016     Eyaya              Partners          pport Staff

                 Pagka’t Yaman ito                  Cecilia Banaag

                 ng Sambayanan                      Lemuel Gallogo


                 (Effective Child                   Alyssa Eseque

                 Rearing: Key in                    Armi Grace

                 Nation Building)                   Desingano


                 2019


                 VALUES                April 13,    MJTalamante        Brgy. Asis I and   Speakers,

                 FORMATION             2019         JCDelEspirituSa  III, Mendez,        Coordinator,

                 SEMINAR                            nto                Cavite            Support Staff,

                                                    RGAPeji                              Facilitators

                                                    MJAAmparo





                                                           62]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[Values                May 24,      MJTalamante        Brgy. Asis I and   Speakers,

                 Reorientation- The    2019         JCDelEspirituSa  III, Mendez,        Coordinator,

                 Choice to Grow                     nto                Cavite            Support Staff,

                                                    ARBDesingano                         Facilitators


                 Drug Awareness         November  MJTalamante          Brgy. Asis I and   Coordinator,

                 Seminar               22, 2019     JCDelEspirituSa  III, Mendez,        Support Staff,

                                                    nto                Cavite            Facilitators

                                                    MJAmparo


                                                    ARBDesingano

                 2020


                 Psychological First   January      Psychology         Mendez,           Coordinator,

                 Aid during TAAL       2020         Faculty            Alfonso,          PFA Providers

                 Erupt                              Members            Indang,           Staff,

                                                                       Bailen,and        Facilitators

                                                                       Magallanes


                 Psychological First   March202     Psychology         All               Coordinator,

                 Aid and Counseling    up to        Faculty                              PFA Providers


                 Sessions              present      Members                              Staff,
                 CASmustahan 2020                                                        Facilitators


                 sa Gitna ng COVID-

                 19 Quarantine

                 Free Confidential

                 Psychosocial





                                                           63]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[Support and

                 Psychological First

                 Aid by CvSU


                 Psychology

                 Professionals

                 Webinar: Usaping      July 1,      Psychology         CAS Students,     Speakers,

                 Lusog Isip sa         2020         Faculty            parents           Coordinator,


                 Panahon ng                         Members                              Support Staff,
                 Covid-19 : CASama                                                       Facilitators


                 mo kami

                 Webinar on Mental     October      DSSH Faculty       Barangay Asis 1   Speakers,


                 Health Awareness      24, 2020     members            and 3, Mendez,    Coordinator,

                                                                       Cavite            Support Staff,

                                                                                         Facilitators






























                                                           64]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[2.2 ADEQUATE AND RELEVANT PROJECTS/ACTIVITIES TO ACHIEVE OBJECTIVES


                       The College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) recognizes the importance of fulfilling the

               university’s function on research and extension. CAS supports this by conducting basic and


               applied  research  to  respond  to  the  needs  of  the  university,  the  college  and  nearby

               communities. The college also conducts needs assessment to identify gaps to be addressed

               in  the  target  communities  for  extension.  Results  of  assessment  were  used  to  identify

               possible  courses  of  interventions  by  the  college.  Furthermore,  this  provides  prospective

               beneficiaries with the needed knowledge and skills to create change in their own lives, their


               families, and the community as well.

                       In line with this, the college is able to develop and generate the basic technologies,

               process and systems and programs that can be transferred to the communities that most

               need  them.      Considering  the  college’s  Community  Adoption  Services:  Kabarangay

               Kaeskwela  for  Indang  Habitat  Gangneung  Pine  Village  (CAS:  KK  for  IHGPV)  project,  the


               following extension programs were identified:


               CAS KK for Indang Habitat Gangneung Pine Village


                       1.  Alalay sa Kabataan – Kaunlaran sa Kinabukasan


                       2.  Pagpapahalaga sa Sarili Pagpapaunlad sa Pamayanan: Values

                          Reorientation


                       3.  Flying Math para sa Kabuhayan


                       4.  Iba Na Ang Handa (Project INAH)


                       5.  Edible Landscaping


                       6.  Good Governance for Prosperity





                                                           65]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[The following extension projects were also identified in CAS-CARES-SOCSCI-


               Psychosocial Services Yearning towards Community Health and Wellness (PSYCH)


               Component 1: Personal Functioning


                       Activity 1. Values Formation Seminar-Workshop


                       Activity 2. Values Reorientation Seminar-Workshop


               Component 2: Psychological Functioning


                       Activity 1. Psychological First Aid and Seminar Workshop Activity


                       Activity 2. Mental Health Awareness Seminar Activity


                       Activity 3. Drug Awareness Campaign Seminar


               Component 3: Social Functioning


                       Activity 1. Parenting Seminar


                       Activity 2. Conflict Resolution Seminar


                       2.2.1 Technical Service Consultancy


                       The  extension  programs  and  activities  of  the  Department  of  Social  Sciences  and


               Humanities are based on the knowledge and skills gained from the program BS Psychology,

               research completed and needs, problems and resources of the clients. They are also based

               on the department, college, and university extension thrusts.


                       For  the  past  five  years,  the  department  headed  by  its  chair  has  implemented  the


               following extension programs/projects/activities:

               1. Values Reorientation




                                                           66]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[2. Couple Empowerment


               3.  Psychosocial Services Yearning towards Community Health and Wellness (PSYCH)


               Project

               4. Psychological First Aid


               In all these projects, faculty members’ and students’ expertise is utilized for the conduct of


               extension activities. Several faculty members serve as consultants, speakers, coordinators,

               facilitators and support staff for the abovementioned community projects.


                       2.2.2  Technology Dissemination


               The department continues to cater to the needs of its clientele in the form of seminars and


               training. The following seminars and trainings were conducted:


               For Values Reorientation:


                    ●  The Choice to Grow


                    ●  The Choice to Give


                    ●  The Choice to Listen


                    ●  The Choice to Make a Difference


                    ●  The Choice to Do What is Right


                    ●  The Choice to Take Care of



               Yourself For Couple Empowerment:


                    ●  Si Ako… Si Ikaw… Iba ma’y Pinag-isa (Gender Differences)







                                                           67]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[●  Kahinaa’y Lakas, Kabigua’y Tagumpay Ikaw at Ako Magkaagapay (Art of Conjugal

                       Harmony: Handling Marital Conflicts make it easy)


                    ●  Anak na Biyaya Aalagaan, Pagkat Yaman ito ng Sambayanan (Effective Child


                       Rearing: Key in Nation Building)


               Psychosocial Services Yearning towards Community Health and Wellness (PSYCH)


                    ●  Component 1: Personal Functioning

                       Activity 1. Values Formation Seminar-Workshop

                       Activity 2. Values Re-Orientation Seminar-Workshop

                    ●  Component 2: Psychological Functioning



                       2. Mental Health Awareness Seminar Activity

                       3. Drug Awareness Campaign Seminar

                       These  capacity  enhancement  training  mentioned  above  were  all  attended  by  the

               home partners of IHGPV and the communities of Brgy Asis 1 and 3 Mendez, Cavite and

               disseminated  through  announcement  in  barangay  meetings  and  assembly  and  giving  out

               brochures.


               Psychological First Aid Orientation and Training during TAAL Eruption


                       As  Taal  Volcano  erupted,  the  Psychology  faculty  members  spearheaded  the

               Psychological First Aid Orientation and Training last January 21 and 23, 2020. The speaker

               for the said training was Dr. Paulito V. Hilario and Dr. Cecilia B. Banaag, faculty members of


               the  Psychology  program.  They  are  Registered  Guidance  Counselor  and  Registered

               Psychologist.  The  first  training  was  attended  by  134  participants  composed  of  students,

               graduate school students and alumni. The second training was participated by 36 attendees






                                                           68]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[from both teaching and non-teaching staff of CVSU main and satellite campuses. Evacuees

               in Mendez, Alfonso, Indang, Bailen, and Magallanes are the recipients of the PFA services.

               Aside from the PFA, donations and food packs were also given to help the Municipal Social


               Welfare Division in assisting the Taal evacuees.


               CASmustahan 2020 sa Gitna ng COVID- 19 Quarantine

               Free Confidential Psychosocial Support and Psychological First Aid by

               CvSU Psychology Professional

                       As Cavitenos continues recovering from the TAAL eruption, the COVID-19 pandemic


               starts its way of harming people’s lives. The immediate spread of this virus put the different

               areas not just in the country but also worldwide into Enhanced Community Quarantine. As

               the virus spreads different mental health problems such as fears and anxiety arises. With

               that,  Psychology  Instructors  made  use  of  their  skills  and  knowledge  in  conducting

               Psychological  First  Aid.  From  March  2020  to  June  2020,  258  individuals  were  given


               Psychosocial Support and Psychological First Aid.

               Webinar: Usaping Lusog Isip sa Panahon ng Covid-19 : CASama mo kami


               With the support and encouragement of Dr. Bettina Joyce P. Ilagan, Dean of the College of

               Arts  and  Sciences,  the  Psychology  Program  Extension  unit  conducted  an  online


               “CASmustahan” which also served as a semi-webinar with question and answer in promoting

               mental  health  and  teaching  students,  colleagues  and  other  stakeholders  in  mental  and

               emotional self-care during the time of the COVID-19 pandemic. The July 1 activity, which

               was  held  through  the  online  platform  Zoom  and  was  broadcasted  live  through  Facebook,

               lasted for two (2) hours with eight thousand three hundred views (8300) and one hundred


               thirty two(132) shares.








                                                           69]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[Webinar on Mental Health Awareness


                    The  extension  program  of  CVSU-CAS-DSSH  responded  and  reached-out  through

               Social Distancing, Quarantine Program and other ordinances restricted physical contact and

               limited  the  program  that  the  extension  services  can  offer.  But  those  factors  instead  of

               obstructing the plans, it became a means to repackage the extension activities in a flexible

               way. Last October 24, 2020 a Webinar on Mental Health was held via Facebook live. It was


               mainly for the Barangay Officials and Front liners and the community of Barangay Asis 1 and

               3    but  invitation  was  extended  to  other  communities  and  individuals  because  of  the

               relevance of the topic.it garnered two thousand eight hundred (2800) views and ninety one

               (91) shares in Facebook.










































                                                           70]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[Brochures used to disseminate relevant information about seminars conducted









































                                                           71]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[CvSU website recognizing the PFA Orientation and training held














                                                           72]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[73]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[Research Development and Extension Office bulletin board where updates are posted and

                                   articles in “Ugnayan” about CAS extension activities
































                                                           74]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[2.3 SYSTEMATIC AND EFFECTIVE PROCEDURES


                       In  consonance  with  the  standard  operating  procedures  being  implemented  in  the

               University, the diagram (Figure 1) below serves as the general guide in the implementation


               of the extension projects. Research and extension projects shall be properly endorsed by

               the concerned  office  or authority to  the  University  Research,  Development  and  Extension

               (RDE) Council for recommendation to the President. A Memorandum of Understanding or

               Memorandum  of  Understanding  (MOA/MOU)  shall  be  executed  for  projects  involving

               external partners. Research / extension project implemented are required to be presented


               during the agency in-house review and evaluation.

































               Figure 1.General process flow of research and extension program implementation.


                       The  College  of  Arts  and  Sciences  is  manned  with  competent  and  dynamic  Dean,


               Research and Extension Coordinators and faculty task force who ensure that the target



                                                           75]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[Research  and  Extension  projects  are  properly  implemented.  Through  proper  consultation

               and coordination with the University Research and Extension Center, the college has been


               actively facilitating extension projects.

               To  make  the  extension activities  sustainable  and  continuing,  DSSH  adopted the following

               strategies:


                   A.  Conceptualization and Preparation


               This phase covers the time preparation from the  conceptualization of the target extension

               project, preparation and endorsement of the proposals and documents for approval to the

               concerned  offices/units,  and  creation  of  Extension  task  force  committee  involving  the


               students and community partners prior to its implementation.

                   B.  Implementation Proper


               For a systematic and effective procedure on the implementation of the extension projects,


               the following are followed:

                   1.  Consultation  meetings  with  barangay  council  members  and  others  concerned  like

                       school principals. Consultative meetings with the municipal mayor, barangay council

                       members,  school  principals  and  other  stakeholders  were  done to  discuss  possible

                       collaborations.


                   2.  Community  Needs  Assessment.  Needs  of  the  community  were  assessed  thru

                       surveys  and  interviews.  The  survey  was  done  in  every  other  house  by  asking

                       questions guided by a questionnaire.











                                                           76]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[3.  Consultative Meetings with the target beneficiaries and Presentation of Extension

                       Project proposal


                   4.  MOA/MOU signing


                   5.  Coordination with the CvSU Extension Services


                   6.  Project Launching


                   7.  Project implementation


                   C. Monitoring and Evaluation


               The  University  Extension  Center  has  devised  a  monitoring  and  evaluation  form  that  is

               administered to the clientele to  determine the strengths and weaknesses of the extension

               project and identify possible improvement.


               Monitoring and evaluation of the progress of the projects


               Impact assessment of extension project































                                                           77]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[Community Adoption Series: Kabarangay at Kaeskwela (CAS: KK) headed by Dr. Lynn G.

               Penales (CAS Dean) with the different extension coordinators from the departments of the


               college.






















                                                           78]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[College Research and Extension Team during one of the meetings for R&E Planning.


































                                                           79]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[Consultative Meeting with the Vice President for Research and Extension












                                                           80]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[81]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[MOA and MOU







                                                           82]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[MOA signing of Daine Officials and Dean Bettina Joyce P. Ilagan with Psychology

                                                 Instructors and students















                                                           83]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[2.4 REASONABLE BUDGET


                       To  ensure  the  effective  implementation  of  the  extension  activities,  the  University

               Administration  allocates  adequate  budget  for  its  extension  activities.  Table  2.2  shows  the


               budgetary  allocation  for  the  conduct  of  extension  projects  and  its  actual  expenditures

               covering the year 2013 to 2017. The college allocates from its MOOE for the research and

               extension activities (Table 2.3). The department (DSSH) also allot a portion of its fund to


               support its extension activities

               Table 2.2 Budgetary allocation for the conduct of University extension projects and

               actual expenditures for the year 2013 to 2017 (in thousand pesos).


               Source: Financial Reports of the University Accounting




                            CY 2013         CY 2014         CY 2015         CY 2016         CY 2017




                            All      Actu   All      Actu   All      Actu   All      Actu   All      Actu
                            oc      al      oc      al      oc      al      oc      al      oc      al
                            ati      Expe   ati      Expe   ati      Expe   ati      Expe   ati      Expe
                            on      nditur   on      nditur   on      nditur   on      nditur   on      nditur
                                    es              es              es              es              es



                  Purcha    12,     12,     46,     45,     48,     48,44   14      135,3   15      153,6
                  se of     24      914     33      712     38      1       5,2      41     7,0      11
                  instruct   5              9               6               57              78
                  ional
                  equipm
                  ent,
                  supplie
                  s,
                  materia
                  ls,
                  facilitie
                  s, etc.


                  Condu     7,      11,66   8,5     11,11   10,     9,101   15,     15,46   11,     11,43
                  ct of     00      0       00      0       95              99      0       58      2
                  Resear    0                               5               5               3
                  ch




                                                           84]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[Condu     45     563      1,1    815      1,1    1,149    4,2    3,666    9,9    2,075
                  ct of     0               50              50              58              32
                  Extensi
                  on
                  Project
                  s



                  Improv    4,0    3,234    6,8    6,770    7,8    6,826    6,8    10,72    9,4    6,116
                  ement     00              00              21              00     7        90
                  of
                  library
                  holding
                  s/
                  service
                  s/faciliti
                  es


                  Repair    1,7    2,117    1,7    1,502    1,7    1,543    18,    16,94    16,    16,46
                  of        00              00              00              64     5        21     9
                  physic                                                    5               9
                  al
                  facilitie
                  s and
                  laborat
                  ories



                  Faculty   3,2    3,592    3,6    2,909    4,5    4,556    6,5    7,225    1,2    1,822
                  and       15              00              92              19              78
                  Staff
                  Develo
                  pment



                  Faculty   26,    24,47    47,    45,76    56,    45,18    66,    59,63    44,    44,58
                  and       20     1        20     9        00     8        97     6        04     6
                  Staff     0               0               0               2               9
                  Incenti
                  ves
                  and
                  benefit
                  s


                  Auxiliar   1,8   1,631    1,8    1,869    1,8    1,869    1,8    1,870    1,9    1982
                  y         70              70              70              70              82
                  Service
                  s



                  Others    -      -        -      -








                                                           85]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[TOTAL     56,    60,18    11     116,4    13     118,6    26     250,8    25     238,0
                            68     2        7,1    56       2,4    73       6,3    70       1,6    93
                            0               59              74              16              11



               Table 2.3 Budgetary allocation for the conduct of college extension activities from
               2013 – 2019.


                  AREA OF      2013       2014        2015       2016       2017        2018      2019

                  CONCERN



                  Supplies     P150,00    P150,00     P327,00    P300,65    P273,00     265,80    352,74

                               0.00       0.00        0.00       6.00       0.00        0.00      0.87



                  Communic     P17,000.   P17,000.    P19,000.   P18,000.   P43,000.    18,000.   21,600.

                  ation        00         00          00         00         00          00        00



                  Travel       P40,000.   P50,000.    P115,00    P42,000.   P50,000.    50,000.   50,000.

                               00         00          0.00       00         00          00        00



                  Printing     P85,000.   P130,00     P80,000.   P100,00    P60,000.    60,000.   40,000.

                               00         0.00        00         0.00       00          00        00



                  Research     P100,00    P70,000.               P80,000.   P80,000.    80,000.   60,000.

                               0.00       00                     00         00          00        00
                                                      P45,000.


                                                      00

                  Extension    P100,00    P70,000.               P40,000.   P80,000.    80,000.   60,000.

                               0.00       00                     00         00          00        00



                  Faculty      P100,00    P100,00                P64,344.   P43,000.    150,00    111,65
                  Developme    0.00       0.00                   00         00          0.00      9.13

                  nt



                  General      P56,000.   P56,000.    P50,000.   P100,00    P100,00     18,000.   20,000.

                  Services     00         00          00         0.00       0.00        00        00











                                                           86]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[Repair and   P29,000.   P34,000.    P50,000.   P15,000.   P31,000.    31,900.   32,000.
                  Maintenan    00         00          00         00         00          00        00
                  ce


                  Others       P70,000.   P114,00     P114,00    -          -                     52,000.
                               00         0.00        0.00                                        00



                  TOTAL        P760,00    P800,00     P800,00    P760,00    P760,00
                               0.00       0.00        0.00       0.00       0.00




















































                                                           87]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[88]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[2.5 PROVISION OF MATERIALS AND OTHER RESOURCES


                              The University ensures that materials, supplies, and other resources are


                       made available for the implementation of the extension project.


                       The college provides materials and other resources from its MOOE for research and

                       extension activities. The budget is shared by the different departments of the college.


                       College of Arts and Sciences also hold income-generating activities from time to time.

                       Some  of  the  already  successfully  finished  ones  are  Takbo  mga  CASama,  CASKK
                       Serenades  and  Artistas  Y  Artistahins  V.2.0.  Proceeds  of  the  abovementioned

                       activities were utilized for the implementation and conduct extension projects.



                       Table  2.4  shows  the  agencies/unit/office  and  participants  who  have  provided


                       assistance  and  support  in  order  to  implement  the  extension  program  of  the

                       department.  Table  2.5  lists  the  agencies  that  serve  as  national  and  regional

                       extension linkages of the university.

                       Table 2.4 List of Agency/Unit/Office and Participants that provide support and

                       assistance in the implementation of extension programs of the department.

                                                   NATURE OF                     PROVISION /
                       AGENCY/UNIT/OFFICE
                                                   PARTICIPATION                 ASSISTANCE


                          1.  CvSU-CAS-DSSH        Proponent                         ●  Faculty and

                                                                                         students

                                                                                         developed

                                                                                         projects

                                                                                     ●  Faculty

                                                                                         members, staff

                                                                                         and students

                                                                                         during planning

                                                                                         and actual

                                                                                         extension

                                                                                         activities



                                                                89]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[●  Teaching or

                                                                                         training materials

                                                                                     ●  Venue for

                                                                                         planning



                           2. LGU-Indang           Cooperating Agency                ●  Venue for

                                                                                         planning



                           3. LGU – Barangay       Adopted Barangay                  ●  Full support and

                              Daine 2                                                    participation of

                                                       ●  Pre-planning activity          the Barangay

                                                                                         Captain and
                                                       ●  Completion of plans            other officials and

                                                       ●  Implementation of              the community

                                                           Plans                         members

                                                                                     ●  Venue for

                                                                                         trainings/seminar

                                                                                         s and the actual

                                                                                         implementation

                                                                                         of the extension

                                                                                         activities



                           4. Kiwanis Club-        Collaborating Agency              ●  Provision of

                              Treasures of                                               Technical

                              Indang                                                     Support during

                                                                                         sessions, in

                                                                                         terms of

                                                                                         registration,

                                                                                         photo/video

                                                                                         coverage,

                                                                                         sharing of

                                                                                         experiences and

                                                                                         feeding

                                                                                         programs.

                                                                                     ●  Linkaging for

                                                                                         other resources

                                                                                     ●  Additional

                                                                                         support such as

                                                                                         snacks, supplies,
                                                                                         and other related

                                                                                         activities to the

                                                                                         program

                           5. Daine Western        Collaborating Agency              ●  provision of its

                              Cavite Institute                                           classroom and

                                                                                         other facilities.

                                                                                         venues for

                                                                                         various learning

                                                                                         sessions and

                                                                                         other activities of

                                                                                         the program

                                                               90]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[●  provision of
                                                                                         possible resource
                                                                                         persons and
                                                                                         linkaging for
                                                                                         other resources
                          6.  i-HOME Indang        Collaborating Agency              ●  provision of
                                                                                         IHGPV data.
                                                                                         provide
                                                                                         necessary data
                                                                                         of IHGPV home
                                                                                         partners and their
                                                                                         family for
                                                                                         program
                                                                                         planning/impleme
                                                                                         ntation and
                                                                                         monitoring
                                                                                     ●  Linkaging for
                                                                                         other resources.




                       Table 2.5 List of university extension linkages


                                                                                   NATURE OF
                       AGENCY              ADDRESS             LEVEL
                                                                                   LINKAGE



                       DEPED –             Cainta, Manila      Regional            Education Alliance

                       Calabarzon



                       SUCs (32            Nationwide          National            Education Alliance

                       nationwide)



                       CHED                Diliman, Quezon,    National            Education Alliance

                                           City



                       Select Connect      South Korea         International       Funding/Cooperating

                       Union                                                       Agency






                       2.6 PARTICIPATION OF SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF FACULTY /
                       STAFF/ STUDENTS / COMMUNITY IN MAJOR PROJECTS/ACTIVITIES

                       Extension projects conducted by DSSH – BS Psychology Unit in the last five years
                       were participated by several students, faculty members and staff, administration, and

                       members of the community involved (Table 2.6). The conduct of meetings, planning,
                                                               91]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[collection  of  data,  outlining  of  memorandum  of  understanding  and  actual  project

                       implementation were all participated by the above-mentioned group of people.


                       As a whole, the college has maintained the culture of camaraderie and solidarity in


                       the implementation and completion of various extension projects. With the dean and

                       coordinators  directly  involved  in  the  supervision  and  monitoring,  the  extension

                       projects under review were products of the concerted efforts of everyone involved.


                       Table 2.6. DSSH BS Psychology extension projects and activities from 2013-


                       2020)


                         Title of the     Date        Faculty And        Clientele       Nature of
                         activity                     Students           /Beneficia      Involvement
                                                      Involved           ry

                         2013

                         CAS: KK for      Decem       Mary Joyce         IHGPV           Facilitator,
                         IHGPV            ber 14,     Eyaya              Home            Support Staff
                         MOU              2013        BS                 Partners
                         SIGNING                      Psychology
                                                      students

                         2014

                         Si Ako, Si       Februa      Mary Joyce         IHGPV           Coordinator,
                         Ikaw: Iba        ry 8,       Eyaya              Home            Facilitator,
                         ma’y             2014        Mary Jane          Partners        Support Staff
                         Pinag-isa        and         Amparo
                          Gender          Februa      Louziela
                         Differences      ry 25,      Masana
                                          2014        Imelda Filart
                                                      Ana Ruth
                                                      Andalajao

                                                       BS
                                                      Psychology
                                                      students







                                                               92]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[Values           August      Mary Joyce         IHGPV           Speaker,

                         Reorientatio     10,         Eyaya              Home            Coordinator,

                         n Part 1.        2014        Czherie Fei        Partners        Facilitator,

                         “The Choice                  Ledesma                            Support Staff

                         to Grow”                     Cecilia

                         Ako sa                       Banaag

                         Pangarap                      BS

                         kong Buhay                   Psychology

                                                      students



                         Values           Octobe      Mary Joyce         IHGPV           Coordinator,S

                         Reorientatio     r 5,        Eyaya              Home            upport Staff

                         n Part 2.        2014        Mary Jane          Partners
                         “The Choice                  amparo

                         to Give”
                                                       BS

                                                      Psychology

                                                      students



                         Values           Octobe      Maty Joyce         IHGPV           Coordinator,S

                         Reorientatio     r 12,       Eyaya              Home            upport Staff

                         n Part 3.        2014        Joy Babaan         Partners

                         “The Choice                  Mary Jane

                         to Listen”                   Amparo

                                                       BS

                                                      Psychology

                                                      students



                         2015



                         “Art of          Februa      Mary Joyce         IHGPV           Coordinator,S

                         Conjugal         ry 15,      Eyaya              Home            upport Staff

                         Harmony:         2015        Mary Jane          Partners

                         Marital                      Amparo
                         Conflicts                    Ana Ruth

                         Make it                      Andalajao

                         Easy...                       BS

                         Kahinaa’y                    Psychology

                         Lakas,                       students
                         Kabigua’y

                         Tagumpay,

                         Ikaw at Ako

                         Magkaagap

                         ay”







                                                               93]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[Values           Februa      Mary Joyce         IHGPV           Coordinator,S

                         Reorientatio     ry 22,      Eyaya              Home            upport Staff

                         n Part 4         2015        Mary Jane          Partners

                         SSS                          Amparo

                         PAGIBIG:                     Joy Babaan

                         Sustaining,                   BS

                         Strengtheni                  Psychology

                         ng and                       students

                         Satisfying

                         one’s

                         Relationship



                         Values           March       Mary Joyce         IHGPV           Coordinator,S
                         Reorientatio     1, 2015     Eyaya              Home            upport Staff

                         n Part V:                    Mary Jane          Partners

                         “The Choice                  Amparo

                         to Make a                    Ana Ruth
                         Difference:                  Andalajao

                         She says,                     BS

                         He says,                     Psychology

                         We say”                      students


                         Values           Sept.       Mary      Joyce    IHGPV           Coordinator,

                         Reorientatio     13,         Eyaya              Home            Facilitator,

                         n Part VI        2015                           Partners        Support Staff

                         “The Choice                  Josephine

                         To Take                      Manapsal

                         Care of
                         Yourself”                    Mary       Jane

                                                      Amparo

                                                      Ma.      Glenda

                                                      Torreda

                                                      Alyssa

                                                      Eseque

                                                      John Christian

                                                      Paolo Belen

                                                      Armi     Grace

                                                      Desingano

                                                      Leonido Orsal

                                                      Jr.

                                                      Renato

                                                      Agdalpen

                                                      Mike Oliver

                                                      Gimao


                                                                94]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[BS

                                                      Psychology

                                                      students


                         “Project         Octobe      CAS         and    IHGPV           Coordinator,

                         Alalay”: Ang     r, 25,      CON      faculty   Home            Facilitator,

                         malusog na       2015        members            Partners        Support Staff

                         NANAY, sa

                         Tahana’y                     BS

                         Matagumpa                    Psychology

                         y na                         students

                         Kaagapay


                         2016



                         Year 3:          Februa      Mary      Joyce    IHGPV           Coordinator,S

                         Anak na          ry 28,      Eyaya              Home            upport Staff

                         Biyaya           2016                           Partners

                         Aalagaan,                    Cecilia

                         Pagka’t                      Banaag

                         Yaman ito
                         ng                           Lemuel

                         Sambayana                    Gallogo

                         n (Effective

                         Child                        Alyssa

                         Rearing:                     Eseque

                         Key in

                         Nation                       Armi     Grace

                         Building)                    Desingano

                                                      BS

                                                      Psychology

                                                      students



                         2019



                           VALUES         April       MJTalamante        Brgy. Asis      Speakers,

                          FORMATIO        13,                            I and III,      Coordinator,
                         N SEMINAR        2019        JCDelEspiritu      Mendez,         Support Staff,


                                                      Santo              Cavite          Facilitators

                                                      RGAPeji

                                                      MJAAmparo






                                                               95]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[BS

                                                      Psychology

                                                      students



                                                      MJTalamante

                            Values        May         JCDelEspiritu      Brgy. Asis      Speakers,

                         Reorientatio     24,         Santo              I and III,      Coordinator,

                            n- The        2019        ARBDesingan        Mendez,         Support Staff,

                           Choice to                  o                  Cavite          Facilitators

                             Grow                      BS

                                                      Psychology

                                                      students



                                                      MJTalamante

                             Drug                     JCDelEspiritu      Brgy. Asis      Coordinator,

                          Awareness       Novem       Santo              I and III,      Support Staff,

                           Seminar        ber 22,     MJAmparo           Mendez,         Facilitators

                                          2019       ARBDesingano        Cavite
                                                       BS

                                                      Psychology

                                                      students


                             2020


                                                      Psychology

                          Psychologic     Januar      Faculty            Mendez,         Coordinator,

                          al First Aid    y 2020      Members            Alfonso,        PFA Providers

                         during TAAL                                                     Staff,

                             Erupt                                       Indang,         Facilitators

                                                                         Bailen,and

                                                                         Magallane

                                                                         s



                                                      Psychology

                          Psychologic     March2      Faculty            All             Coordinator,

                          al First Aid    02 up       Members                            PFA Providers

                              and         to                                             Staff,

                          Counseling      present                                        Facilitators

                           Sessions










                                                               96]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[Psychology

                           Webinar:       July 1,     Faculty            CAS             Speakers,

                           Usaping        2020        Members            Students,       Coordinator,

                          Lusog Isip                                     parents         Support Staff,

                          sa Panahon                                                     Facilitators

                         ng Covid-19

                          : CASama

                           mo kami



                                                      DSSH Faculty

                          Webinar on      Octobe      members            Barangay        Speakers,

                            Mental        r 24,                          Asis 1 and      Coordinator,

                            Health        2020                           3, Mendez,      Support Staff,

                          Awareness                                      Cavite          Facilitators





                       2.7 AWARDS OF DISTINCTION/ACHIEVEMENT AND GRANTS OF BS
                       PSYCHOLOGY

                       Awards Received


                       The  college  also  received  an  honor.  CAS:  KK  was  awarded  with  Plaques  of

                       Recognition  for  its  service  to  the  municipality  through  the  college’s  extension

                       activities.  Gawad  Kabalikat  from  the  Office  of  the  Municipal  Mayor  of  Indang  was

                       awarded  to  the  college  for  support  and  help  extended  by  the  college  and  its  four


                       departments to the community.





















                                                               97]]></page><page Index="100"><![CDATA[Awards received by the college

                             extension program.















                                                               98]]></page><page Index="101"><![CDATA[Mr. Dickson Dimero, Dr. Teddy Tepora, Dr. Evelyn Singson, former CAS Dean and


                       Dr. Renato Pelorina with the plaque of Recognition awarded to CAS for its

                       extension project, CAS: KK.





                                                               99]]></page><page Index="102"><![CDATA[Award received from Mendez recognizing the program, Social Organization

                       Through Comprehensive Services and Community Intervention of CAS-DSSH




                                                              100]]></page><page Index="103"><![CDATA[Certificate from Mendez recognizing the college extension program







                                                              101]]></page><page Index="104"><![CDATA[2.8 BEST PRACTICES ADOPTED


                       Extension  is  one  of  the  core  functions  of  higher  education  institutions.  Through


                       extension programs and services, change is affected, and people are empowered in

                       the  community.  The  academe  shares  this  responsibility  of  transferring  technology

                       and enhancing capabilities with the local government by way of training, workshops,

                       seminars and so many others.


                       Adhering  to  this  call  as  well,  Cavite  State  University  offers  different  extension


                       services  which  were  all  geared  towards  promoting  community  improvement  and

                       development. One of which is the Department of Social Sciences and Humanities,

                       BS Psychology Unit’s extension project, Pasya mo Buhay mo which was rendered

                       for 3 years and was continued through the PSYCH Extension Project. The project

                       aimed  at  helping  and  assisting  the  community  of  Indang  Habitat  Gangneung  Pine


                       Village Daine 2 Indang, Cavite and Barangay Asis 1 and 3 Mendez, Cavite and it

                       also aimed to empower the self, women and couples of IHGPV and enhance values

                       reorientation through the Psychological Approach


                       2.8.1 Conduct of Income-Generating Activities


                              The college conducted activities under the CAS: KK project such as “Trick or

                       Treat, CAS Serenades Offices”, “Takbo mga CASama” and Artistas Y Artistahins to

                       source  out  funds.  Such  income-generating  activities  make  every  extension  activity

                       possible, which were all done through the cooperation of all CAS members.


                       2.8.2 Continuous Support of Extension Staff, Faculty and Students


                       The  College  Dean  and  Extension  Head’s  continuous  support  was  felt  by  all  the

                       extension staff and members. Thus, they were highly encouraged to contribute and

                       extend help for the communities to sustain the extension activities.
                                                              102]]></page><page Index="105"><![CDATA[Students  also  actively  participate  and  support  the  program’s  extension  activities.

                       They would provide their expertise in Psychology and extend them to the adopted


                       community.

                       2.8.3 Administrative Support


                              The University has been very supportive of the conduct of its functions, one of

                       which  is  Extension,  through  the  Research  and  Extension  Center.  Aside  from  the

                       funds  or  budget  allocated  for  the  implementation  of  extension  projects,  they


                       themselves  support  extension  activities  from  planning  until  its  monitoring  and

                       evaluation.


                       2.8.4 Active Involvement of Extension Linkages


                       Sourcing-out of funds, materials, technical support and other service inputs for the

                       extension activities were all made possible with the help of the partner agencies that

                       really contributed to the success of CAS: KK.


                       College of Arts and Sciences conducted a joint outreach venture with the Kosmos


                       Technomobile Inc. (Cherry Mobile), through their Maynard S. Ngu Foundation (MSN

                       Foundation), to alleviate the academic needs of students in Mendez Central School

                       and  Asis  Elementary  School.  Through  the  collaborative  effort  of  the  college  and

                       foundation, 250 indigent pupils from Asis Elementary School and 224 from Mendez

                       Central School were awarded with bags, notebooks, and pens. This outreach activity


                       was held on September 10, 2019, with two programs conducted at Asis Elementary

                       School in the morning and at Mendez Central School in the afternoon.








                                                              103]]></page><page Index="106"><![CDATA[Top 3 winners in the “Takbo mga CASama” funrun.






























                                    Participants for Takbo mga CASamagetting ready to run.

                                                              104]]></page><page Index="107"><![CDATA[Amount generated from the serenade.




























                         CAS Dean, Dr. Lynn Penales, DSSH Faculty Members and BS Psychology Students

                                                   serenading offices in CvSU.



                                                              105]]></page><page Index="108"><![CDATA[Artistas y Artistahins, part of the proceeds of this fund-raising event goes to the


                       college’s extension activities







                                                              106]]></page><page Index="109"><![CDATA[Anyare 2014


































                                                              107]]></page><page Index="110"><![CDATA[108]]></page><page Index="111"><![CDATA[anyare 2015







                                                              109]]></page><page Index="112"><![CDATA[Anyare 2016: Anyare 2016: Pagbabalik-Tanaw, Pasasalamat, at Hamon sa

                       Hinaharap:

                                                              110]]></page><page Index="113"><![CDATA[During the culminating activity of CAS:KK IHGPV ANYARE 2016 on January
                       14, 2017, College of Arts and Sciences together with the optometrists and dentists of

                       Alpha  Phi-Omega  Psi  sponsored  dental  and  optical  mission,  wherein  193  reading
                       glasses were distributed and 98 dental patients were served. Antibiotics as well as
                       pain relievers were also provided to patients who have undergone tooth extraction.

                       Midwifery  students  and  faculty  members  of  the  College  of  Nursing  extended  their

                       help by monitoring the vital signs of the patients.





















































                                                              111]]></page><page Index="114"><![CDATA[A  medical,  dental,  and  feeding  program  dubbed  “Sa  Kalusugan  mo,  Kami  ang

               MAAGAP na CASama Mo” was held at Barangay Alulod in cooperation with MAAGAP Inc.
               The event was in response to the request of the community member of Barangay Alulod in
               Indang, Cavite where in 246 clients were served, 87 had undergone tooth extraction, and

               172 were given free medical check-ups and medicines.
























































                                                           112]]></page><page Index="115"><![CDATA[113]]></page></pages></Search>